<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue, arguing that arch-bishops, bishops, curates, neuters, are to be cut-off by the law of God; therefore all these, with their service, are to be castout by the law of the land. Notwithstanding, the world pleads for their own, why some bishops should be spared; the government maintained; the name had in honour still; but the word of God is cleare against all this, for the casting-of-all-forth. The great question is, which way of government now? For two wayes are contended for, The Presbyteriall and Independent: something is said to both these wayes: but we have a sure word for it, that these two wayes are but in shew two, and will assuredly meet in one. Neuters are shewen openly here, and the curse of God upon them. Presented to the Assembly of Divines.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96888</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3486A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E34_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22862</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871850</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871850</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154605</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96888)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154605)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 6:E34[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue, arguing that arch-bishops, bishops, curates, neuters, are to be cut-off by the law of God; therefore all these, with their service, are to be castout by the law of the land. Notwithstanding, the world pleads for their own, why some bishops should be spared; the government maintained; the name had in honour still; but the word of God is cleare against all this, for the casting-of-all-forth. The great question is, which way of government now? For two wayes are contended for, The Presbyteriall and Independent: something is said to both these wayes: but we have a sure word for it, that these two wayes are but in shew two, and will assuredly meet in one. Neuters are shewen openly here, and the curse of God upon them. Presented to the Assembly of Divines.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. P. and M. S. in Gold-Smiths-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By Hezekiah Woodward -- Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: The "4" in the imprint date is crossed out; "Feb. 26: 1643".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154605:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIALOGUE, ARGVING That <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Curates, Neuters,</hi> are to be cut-off by the Law of GOD; Therefore all theſe, with their <hi>Service,</hi> are to be caſt-out by The Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, The world pleads for their own, why ſome <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſhould be ſpared, The Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment maintained; The <hi>name</hi> had in honour ſtill; But the word <hi>of</hi> God <hi>is cleare againſt all this, for the caſting-of-all-forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great Queſtion is, which <hi>way</hi> of Government now? For <hi>two wayes</hi> are contended for, The <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> and <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent:</hi> Something is ſaid to both theſe <hi>wayes:</hi> But we have a <hi>ſure word for it, That theſe</hi> two wayes <hi>are but in ſhew</hi> two, <hi>and will aſſuredly meet in</hi> one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neuters</hi> are ſhewen openly here, and the curſe of GOD upon them.</p>
            <p>Preſented to the Aſſembly of DIVINES.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>And the</hi> Lord <hi>hath given a Commandement concerning thee, That no more of Thy name ſhall be ſowen: I will make thy grave, for thou art vile.</hi> 
               <bibl>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. 1. 14</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Sing unto the</hi> LORD, <hi>for He has don excellent things; This is knowne in all the earth.</hi> 
               <bibl>Iſa. 12. 5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon mount Zion ſhall be deliverance, and there ſhall be holineſſe.</hi> 
               <bibl>Obad. 17.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>They have made themſelves vile, cast them out of My ſight, and let them goe forth.</hi> 
               <bibl>1 Sam. 3 13. Jer 15. 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that thou ſtoodſt on the other ſide, A looker-on the day of thy brother; even thou waſt one of them.</hi> 
               <bibl>Obad. 11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. P.</hi> and <hi>M. S.</hi> in <hi>Gold-Smiths-Alley,</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:154605:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154605:2"/>
            <head>TO THE EXCELLENT IN THE LAND, D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> VVILLIAM TWISSE, Maſter of the ASSEMBLY: And to the DIVINES there: VVith the moſt highly honoured, and dearly beloved, The Commiſſioners for the Church of <hi>SCOTLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N unknowne perſon, (and deſires ſo to be) the meaneſt of many Thouſands, preſents theſe papers to your hands, which he call a Booke, having (he doubts not) <hi>Truth and reaſon for its Parrons</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Libri, hoc nomine dignandi, in verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis tantum et rationis clientelam ſe dare debent. Ver. de Aug. l</hi> 1.</note>; Therefore he does not doubt, but yee will be its Patrons too; yee will countenance theſe, where-ever you find them, though amidſt ſome refuſe, bearing GODS Image and ſuperſcription. For the man, you will weigh him with his full allowance,
<pb facs="tcp:154605:3"/> he needs all that, and he looks for no more. So far as he dares truſt <hi>a great Deceiver,</hi> he dares ſay, That he has no other end in this, but the glory of GOD, and good of his brother: That he may be informed, if ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant; confirmed, if weake; convinced, if froward and obſtinate, That is the <hi>White</hi> he levells at. There are Three maine Exceptions. 1) Againſt the Title, <hi>It is a Dialogue.</hi> (2) Againſt the Author, A <hi>knowne enemy to Biſhops,</hi> ſayes <hi>Here-ſay,</hi> a moſt notorious liar. (3) A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>wayes</hi> of worſhip now: For ſome ſay, There be two. I ſhall endeavour to give cleare ſatisfaction to all this in the next Pages. I ceaſe here to interrupt you any farther, ſo fixed upon your worke, <hi>Earneſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for the faith;</hi> and <hi>ſtriving together</hi> each with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and for other, <hi>in your prayers</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the good will of Him, That now dwells in the <hi>Buſh,</hi> dwell in your Aſſembly (upon that <hi>glory</hi> let That <hi>defence</hi> be) and in your houſes, To ſupply your abſence, and all needs there; In your ſeverall Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and be a <hi>ſmall Sanctuary</hi> there; In your hearts, and be Lord and King there, <hi>Amen.</hi> The GOD of Truth, lead you into all Truth, <hi>Amen. The Lord of Peace Himſelfe, give you peace alwayes by all meanes, That no occaſion be given to the Adverſary to ſpeake reproachfully,</hi> Amen. <hi>The</hi> LORD <hi>be with you all,</hi> Amen. Take you by the hand, keepe you in His <hi>way,</hi> hold you faſt to it for the Churches good, and your owne good everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:154605:3"/>
            <head>By way of<hi> Preface </hi>to all that love<hi> Truth </hi>and<hi> Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat is, To all over the Chriſtian world, for all love <hi>Peace.</hi> No; There is a generation of men, That ſhall leave their names to poſteritie for a curſe, who <hi>love Death,</hi> ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Battle Aray againſt the Truth, and are preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to <hi>peace,</hi> no more, they hate it in their hearts. I doe not feare to point-out theſe men, and to tell, who they are; They, who ſtand-up for <hi>Arch-biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Lord-Biſhops,</hi> (I call them by that common name, though <hi>Prelate</hi> ſeemes a more proper name) They will maintaine the Government by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and their ſervice in <hi>full force</hi> and <hi>vertue,</hi> as it followes in our Briefes, <hi>Notwithſtanding that there is all law and reaſon againſt it:</hi> And, which is above all Reaſon, though the <hi>LORD CHRIT</hi> has taken to <hi>Himſelfe power</hi> in all the peoples ſight, bringing theſe men downe, even to the <hi>ſides of the pitt,</hi> whence they ſhall not returne, till they riſe to Judgement. The common people lookers on now, and obſerving the Princes and Nobles of the world, in this eager contention, <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> (with the Divell) and <hi>ſtaking</hi> downe <hi>Earldomes,</hi> and <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> and the <hi>crowne</hi> of their <hi>glory;</hi> cannot be perſwaded in their hearts, That this <hi>betting</hi> and <hi>ſtaking</hi> is to winne a very triſte; to gaine a thing of nought. Therefore, having ſuch examples before them, They ſtand-up for <hi>Biſhops</hi> alſo, for their Government, and ſervice: And ſome of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, not <hi>common men</hi> amongst the <hi>commons,</hi> give their reaſon, why they would have <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> neither their Government, nor their <hi>ſervice</hi> aboliſhed; <q>Becauſe, Their <note place="margin">No wiſe Reaſon from ſo wiſe-men.</note> forefathers were born &amp; dyed under the <hi>Biſhops</hi> Government, ſerved <hi>God</hi> after the <hi>Biſhops</hi> manner, and preſcribed formes of worſhip: and why ſhould they yeeld to alterations, or ſubſcribe their names to a <hi>Covenant,</hi> touching that matter?</q> For theſe mens ſakes, whom I tender as brethren, All made of the <hi>ſame bloud;</hi> have all the like precious ſoules; bought with the ſame price; profeſſors of the ſame faith; called all by the ſame <hi>name;</hi> ſeeme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce under the ſame hope; looke to inherit the ſame kingdome; for their ſakes, I have taken this paines; To ſhew them, that will not ſhut their eyes, the cleare <hi>will</hi> and <hi>law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> touching the fore-mentioned, The <hi>throwing downe</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> (I carry it no higher) the <hi>rooting-out</hi> of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; The <hi>caſting-out</hi> of their ſervice; The <hi>aboliſhing</hi> of their name.
<pb facs="tcp:154605:4"/> There be three maine <hi>exceptions</hi> now, as was ſaid, Ile tell what they are, and remove them as I can.</p>
            <p>
               <q>(1.) <hi>It is a Dialogue:</hi> and therein I diſpute and argue the caſe with my ſelfe; and ſo wiſe I am, I will put no other arguments to my ſelfe, but what I can tell my ſelfe how to anſwer: And ſo I muſt needs overcome, as the <hi>Boy</hi> muſt winne the game, that playes with himſelfe. To this I make anſwer firſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1) I thought A continued diſcourſe not ſo proper as a Dialogue, that the <hi>phancie</hi> might have more libertie to worke upon the underſtanding.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) I can ſay truly, That this is no fained diſputation, but truly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally acted; onely now enlarged with ſuch Objections, and Anſwers, which, upon due conſiderations, I could imagine might be made for the upholding of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> the continuance of their Government, or the <hi>name.</hi> I ſay againe, and as in the <hi>ears of GOD;</hi> That I have, by His good hand on me, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered the preſent Controverſie, and have deſired to take-in, as my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding did ſupply, what I thought could be ſuggeſted, for the maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the fore-mentioned; That I might caſt-out all ſcruples, and cleare the minds of the ignorant, and weake Chriſtians touching theſe matters: So much to the firſt Exception.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>2. The next is, That I am not to be be heard in this Controverſie, for I was alwayes a profeſſed enemy to <hi>Biſhops;</hi> I anſwer firſt</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>1. That I doe not crave Audience; let <hi>GOD</hi> be heard, and <hi>Truth</hi> be heard, and I have enough.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>2. I am an enemy to <hi>Biſhops!</hi> Indeed I am, and ever was (ſince I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them, and my ſelfe) An enemy to them: But no farther, than as they are enemies to their <hi>LORD CHRIST;</hi> (Ile adde) and to themſelves, no farther. But becauſe it is an hard matter, To walke evenly towards men, neither having their perſons in Admiration, becauſe of Advantage; nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning them, becauſe of ſome evill they have don againſt the Church; and ſome cloud of diſgrace, which has over-caſt their pleaſant Sun-ſhine: Becauſe of this, I ſhall ſay a little more; That I beare no ill will to any <hi>Lord-Biſhops</hi> perſon in the world. Ill will! nay, I call <hi>GOD</hi> to record upon my ſoule, That, To lift-up the <hi>Arch-Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Lord-Biſhops (Wren</hi> and <hi>Pearce)</hi> nearer to heaven, I could fall-downe upon the earth, and wallow in the duſt there; I could behave my ſelfe for them, as <hi>for my friend</hi> or <hi>brother;</hi> I could bow-downe heavily for them, as one <hi>that mourneth for his mother;</hi> I ſay, I can <hi>mourne for them;</hi> That I can doe without an <hi>if;</hi> I cannot pray for them, but with an <hi>if.</hi> Ile tell you my reaſon; I have heard, and from the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit</hi> too, <hi>Julian</hi> and <hi>Spira</hi> coupled together, and ſo concluded (from falſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes ſure) That even <hi>Spira</hi> (whom good-men hope to meet in heaven)
<pb facs="tcp:154605:4"/> that <hi>Spira</hi> ſinned as <hi>Julian</hi> did, he fell into that ſinne, which none but the cleare-ſighted man can fall into. Ah <hi>Lord I</hi> ſayes any ſo of <hi>Spira?</hi> What may wee feare touching theſe <hi>Biſhops?</hi> who have played and ſported them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the hole of the <hi>Aspe;</hi> and blundred very neare the brim of the darkeſt dungeon; They have fought againſt <hi>GOD</hi> at noone-day, holding a To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch in their hand, the while: and ſo came-up neare borderers upon them, who <hi>oppoſed of malicious wickedneſſe.</hi> This is ſpoken, <hi>Reader,</hi> for migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Reaſons; The leaſt for to cleare my ſelfe, a <hi>friend to the Biſhops ſoules.</hi> (2) To move all to doe for them, as <hi>Samuel</hi> for <hi>Saul, mourhe for them</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Si non ores gea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as tamen, &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. 20, 21.</note>. (3) And to command our wat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fulneſſe, That wee doe not oppoſe cleare T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uths n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſet our ſelves againſt a common light: for ſomething is in this; <hi>The m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n that were not killed with the plagues, repented not of the works of their hands, that they ſhould not worſhip Devills and Idolls: neither repented they of their mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thers, nor of their ſorceries, nor of their fornications, nor of their theits:</hi> There is ſomething in this: and it is in fight. A good warning to us, That wee doe not ſo and ſo, as <hi>Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> and <hi>Lord-Biſhops</hi> have don; And ſo much to evidence my tendereſt reſpect to their perſons, and to their ſoules.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>3. The third exception; And what way of Government now? Theſe <hi>Diſciplinaries</hi> ſhould have continued the Government of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> till they had eſtabliſhed another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>That is againſt the <hi>method</hi> of <hi>Edification;</hi> The old frame muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken downe firſt, and the Rubbiſh caſt-out, before the new frame can be erected, or ſet-up.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>But here are two wayes of Government Argued for; which way ſhall wee, poore ones, take?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Stay a little, and wee will praiſe <hi>God</hi> firſt, Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, when there were ſo many croſſe and contrary wayes of worſhip, and ſervice, as contrary as are <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Belial;</hi> the Temple of <hi>God,</hi> and of Idolls; Theſe wayes are cleane forſaken, now they ſhall never be trod-in any more: And the people of <hi>God</hi> are pointed unto <hi>two wayes,</hi> ſo agreeable to the word of <hi>God,</hi> comming-up ſo neare to the rule, and cloſing with it, That the moſt cleare-ſighted-men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell which way comes-up neareſt. I would wee could praiſe <hi>God</hi> for this.</p>
               <p>2. Let us, poore ones, be adviſed here, and be wondrous carefull and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, That wee doe not goe our <hi>owne way:</hi> for this is an undoubted Truth, That it is our <hi>owne way,</hi> which does and will cauſe all the trouble to the Church, and to our ſelves <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Here I could ſpeake great words ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> GODS <hi>mouth, againſt Maſter</hi> Randall, <hi>and ſuch like, who will goe their own</hi> way, <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in their own eye, but abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in</hi> GODS <hi>ſight.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>3. Marke wee theſe, that are moſt querulous here, and are readieſt to make Objections; They are ſuch, who would make Diviſions amongst us; They are children of <hi>Belial;</hi> they would be under no yoak; It is their <hi>owne</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:154605:5"/> 
                  <hi>way,</hi> the <hi>way</hi> of their owne hearts, which they contend for, and would walke therein: And that will cauſe all the Trouble. Note this. It is not this <hi>way,</hi> or that <hi>way,</hi> which the people oppoſe; but <hi>GODS way</hi> and Command, which is, That every man ſhould looke to his owne <hi>way,</hi> be Judge there <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Note, That the ſacred Scripture wills us not to judge ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> way, <hi>but our own</hi> way. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 31.</note>, and give account thereof, how agreeable it is to the <hi>Goſpel-way;</hi> Which, <hi>giving ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,</hi> wee wickedly call a <hi>Shrifting</hi> now adayes, and will oppoſe mightily.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>But here are <hi>two wayes</hi> of Government ſtill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>So they ſay, and ſo it ſeemes to be, and but ſeemes; Theſe <hi>two wayes</hi> are but like two ſtreames, taking ſeverall channells, ſo they run croſſe a little time, and then fall into the maine againe, and keepe one way, a direct way for ever <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Booke,</hi> p. 38 40.</note>.</p>
               <p>Three words to him or them, who, with deſire doe deſire, That the <hi>way of worſhip</hi> may be cleared, and quickly reſolved upon. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(1) But conſider, That, in the meane time, if thy heart be right, thou maiſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy ſelfe and thy houſe in a <hi>Church way,</hi> the way of <hi>holineſſe;</hi> What hinders? 2. Thou doſt deſire pure Ordinances, an holy Diſcipline; It is well; But is thy heart fit for all this? Is it <hi>prepared?</hi> Thou hopeſt, <hi>Yes;</hi> It is well; But put it out of queſtion. 3. Thou expectest now, That the <hi>LORD</hi> will make great proviſions for His ſervants; He is preparing a <hi>feaſt</hi> now in His Holy Mountaine, for an holy people; He is indeed; But conſider wee, what have wee don with all our ſtore, that abundance which wee have had, ſpecially theſe foure laſt yeeres? Thoſe ſoule-quickening Ordinances! What have wee don with all that abundance? Certainly, theſe were given unto us, That wee might have life thereby, and have it <hi>in abundance.</hi> Ah <hi>Lord!</hi> I remember now how <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> brings in the Heathen before the Throne of <hi>GOD, accepting</hi> their Judgement, from His m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uth; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nding the knee, and giving glory to Him, that ſits thereon; yet had they but a common light, and never heard of the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> not a word. I ſay not, ſayes he, <hi>Where ſhall the wicked appeare?</hi> But, <hi>where ſhall the Goſpellers appeare?</hi> Who have been lifted-up to heaven by the means of grace, yet were their converſation low, and earth-ward; how low will their fall be? A conſideration, if put home to every mans heart, will throw <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>brimſtone</hi> in thither for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, That he may eſcape it for the time to come, and for ever. Let us conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, What good things wee have; how wee have improoued them; not what wee want and would have, but how wanting wee are to what wee have; I have don Prefacing: Wee muſt heare now what <hi>God</hi> ſayes, and would have don: Then wee will heare what man can ſay; <hi>God</hi> will be heard firſt.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154605:5"/>
            <head>A DIALOGVE, ARGVING That <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Curates, Neuters;</hi> All theſe are to be <hi>cut off</hi> by the Law of GOD; therefore to be <hi>caſt-out</hi> by the Law of the Land.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey that have don the ſame abominations, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting whereof their fathers and brethren, in former ages, have been, by the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> cut off from the <hi>earth;</hi> Theſe ought, by the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> to be Caſt-out of the Land: The Arch-biſhops and Biſhops have committed theſe abominations, for which others, in ancient times, have ſuffered death; Therefore theſe ought to be throwne-out of the Land, by the Law of the Land.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I deny that the Biſhops have committed ſuch abominations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>They have committed the ſame abomination (I will inſtance in particulars) againſt the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Gods worſhip,</hi> which, one man having committed, was, by the command of God, cut off from the earth. <note place="margin">Numb. 15 35<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I am not ſo ſlenderly read, but I know whom you mean by that <hi>one man,</hi> him that gathered <hi>ſticks</hi> upon <hi>the Sabbath,</hi> and was by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God put to death for ſo doing; But you can never prove, that the Arch-biſhops and Biſhops, gathered ſticks upon the <hi>Lords day;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their <hi>graces,</hi> nor their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> would ſtoop ſo low, I am confident of that: And as confident I am, that they did not commit the ſame <hi>Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Your confidence will deceive you, and you muſt forſake it: The Biſhops have committed the ſame abomination with an higher hand, and a more open face. I ſay, the ſame in your ſenſe, Firſt,</p>
               <p n="1">(1) They commanded <hi>Ruſhes</hi> to be gathered againſt the <hi>Lords day:</hi> And when the people ſhould be <hi>preparing</hi> themſelves to their ſolemne addreſſe before the Lord, they were commanded to beſtrew the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154605:6"/> with Ruſhes; A ſervice not worth a ruſh, but a notorious <hi>diſ-ſervice</hi> to the Church, and <hi>ſcorne</hi> to the <hi>Lord</hi> of the <hi>day;</hi> But the Biſhops would ſhew their power.</p>
               <p n="2">(2) The ſame in your ſenſe and underſtanding; The Biſhops com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the people to gather flowers, therewith to plat a garland, and to ſet it upon a <hi>May-pole;</hi> To the intent the people might, upon the <hi>Lords day,</hi> dance about it with more chearfulneſſe. O yee heavens! be aſhoniſhed at this! Never the like diſhonour to the Lord Chriſt, ſince their forefathers platted a crown of Thornes for his head. But I go on.</p>
               <p n="3">(3) The ſame in our ſenſe and true conſtruction; For you muſt not conceive, that the man was ſtoned for <hi>gathering ſticks;</hi> there was more in it then a bare action; there was a <hi>malignancy</hi> in it; As his need might have required, he might have gathered ſticks, and kindled them upon the <hi>Sabbath day</hi> too, and have given a good account for ſo doing: As a more toyleſome work might have been don, and is don upon the <hi>Lords day,</hi> then is ſtrewing of Ruſhes; But there muſt be a command for doing it, if not from GODS mouth, yet from mans <hi>neceſſitie,</hi> that has a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: If you obſerve the Context, this <hi>one man</hi> did <hi>preſumptuouſly;</hi> he needed a fire no more then others of his brethren, yet he would <hi>preſume</hi> above all; he would try the Patience of the <hi>Lord;</hi> and, in ſo doing, he <hi>reproached the Lord,</hi> ſayes the Text: his action was preſumptuous, a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Lord.</hi> The Arch-biſhops and Biſhops did the ſame <hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination;</hi> The ſame! They did more <hi>preſumptuouſly;</hi> They did<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>reproach</hi> the <hi>Lord;</hi> never any, from the beginning of the world to that day, did ſo preſumptuouſly as they did; never did any of the Heathen ſo <hi>reproach</hi> their gods, which yet were no gods, as theſe have <hi>reproached</hi> the <hi>God</hi> of gods, and <hi>Lord</hi> of Lords; and ſo have been an inlet to that fire, which now rageth in the Land; They have been a means (I would take no man off from communing with his owne heart, and enquiring how willing he was <hi>to have it ſo)</hi> They have been a means to make our Land a <hi>Tabhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah; Becauſe of the fire of the Lord amongst us</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Numb. 11. 3.</note>. I demand then, Is the Law of the LORD cleare, for the cutting-off theſe men?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, thoſe that have committed that abomination; but all the Biſhops have not don ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhall have free libertie, to ſpeake-out, and what you have to ſay for them, anon. This is to our purpoſe now; That the <hi>Law</hi> was clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, for the cutting off that <hi>one man;</hi> muoh more for the cutting off theſe men, who were <hi>guides</hi> unto others; had a clearer light than he had; did more <hi>preſumptuouſly,</hi> more <hi>reproached</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> than he did; The clearer the light, the clearer the Judgement; And the clearer God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154605:6"/> Law is againſt them, for the cutting of them off; the clearer the Law of the Land is againſt them, for the caſting of them forth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>But you have charged this upon the King.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Not I, The <hi>King</hi> of Kings has charged this blaſpemy, has laid this burden upon the Kings ſhoulders; yet ſo, as it is not a graine the lighter upon the Biſhops ſhoulders. It is charged upon the King, decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>blaſphemous decree;</hi> upon the Biſhops, <hi>preſcribing</hi> the ſame: Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King, as chiefe <hi>Author;</hi> Upon the Biſhops, as Inſtruments. <hi>Woe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 10. 1. <hi>Vae aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leficiorum tum etiam admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris.</hi> Wo to the Authors of wicked decrees, and to the Miniſters executing the ſame. Iſa. 10. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Trem.</hi> Iſa. 10. 3. Jer. 13. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Act. 9. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>unto both,</hi> ſayes the LORD, <hi>And what will you doe in the day of viſitation, and in the day of deſolation, to whom will they flee for helpe?</hi> They have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed their Sanctuary, polluted their <hi>Lords day,</hi> reproached the LORD of the <hi>Day.</hi> Say unto the King, and to his Biſhops, <hi>Humble your ſelves, ſit downe, for your principalities ſhall come downe,</hi> even the Crowne <hi>of your glory.</hi> And untill the King, chiefe in the treſpaſſe, ſhall ſay ſo much to his own ſoule, and not onely ſay it, but be indeed and in truth humbled for it, giving cleare demonſtrations thereof in all the peoples ſight, till he ſayes ſo, and does ſo humble himſelfe, his good people will be as jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of him, as afraid of him joyning with his Parliament, as the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were of <hi>Paul,</hi> when <hi>he would joyne himſelfe with them;</hi> 
                  <q>They were all afraid of him, and beleeved not that he was a Diſciple; This is he, ſaid they, who compelled the people to blaſpheme, and perſecuted the <hi>Saints</hi> to ſtrange Cities;</q> Therefore <hi>Pauls</hi> repentance was as fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared as his ſin was, and then he was truſted, and not before. I proceed to a ſecond Argument.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>II Argument. <hi>The Biſhops have blaſphemed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>You have ſaid enough, if you can prove that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I prove it firſt, They ſaid they are Biſhops, when they were not; for they did nothing as became Biſhops.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Is it blaſphemy to ſay, <hi>Wee are, what indeed wee are not?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, in Gods account, and He can beſt judge of Blaſphemy; <hi>I know,</hi> ſayes the <hi>Spirit, the blaſphemy of them,</hi> who <hi>ſay they are Jewes, and they</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>are not;</hi> What was their blaſphemy? Surely, wee know no other but this, <hi>They ſaid they were, what they were not;</hi> That was their blaſphemy: And it is of high conſideration, &amp; of the ſame concernment to us Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to teach us <hi>To be, what wee ſay wee are.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>The Biſhops ſaid they are Biſhops, and they are Biſhops, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſee them to be ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, if lawne ſleeves, and an outward dreſſe, or garb, can give in ſufficient evidence, That they are, what they <hi>ſay</hi> they are; But let us, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154605:7"/> to the Charge, ſpeake as the Oracles of GOD, and deliver forth clearly, what they <hi>ſay,</hi> and what wee <hi>ſee:</hi> It is true, the <hi>Lord Chriſt,</hi> who ſees the heart, and knowes the ſecrets therein, does not <hi>judge after the ſight of the eye, nor reprove after the hearing of the eare.</hi> But wee, poore <note place="margin">Iſa. 11. 4.</note> men, who ſee no more but the out-ſide, wee muſt take leave to judge af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſight of the eyes, and reprove (for wee have no other means) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the hearing of our ears: Wee profeſſe heartily, wee marke not ſo much, what men <hi>ſay,</hi> as what they <hi>doe;</hi> Wee care not what they <hi>ſay</hi> they are; but what wee <hi>ſee</hi> they are; And ſo wee will compare what they <hi>ſay</hi> they are, and what wee <hi>ſee</hi> they are, and ſo leave it to others, thereby to give Righteous Judgement; They <hi>ſay</hi> they are from heaven; wee <hi>ſee</hi> they are from <hi>Rome.</hi> They <hi>ſay</hi> they are Fathers; wee <hi>ſee</hi> they have no natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affection at all; <hi>bloudy Fathers</hi> have they been, <hi>bloudy Fathers.</hi> They <hi>ſay</hi> they are ſpirituall; wee <hi>ſee</hi> they are altogether carnall. They <hi>ſay</hi> they are <hi>Lords;</hi> wee <hi>ſee</hi> they are ſlaves to their luſts, to their honours, to men, Time-ſervers, Men-pleaſers. They <hi>ſay</hi> they are <hi>ovex-ſeers;</hi> wee <hi>ſee</hi> they <hi>over-ſee</hi> nothing but their Rents and Revennewes, which was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint long agoe <note n="b" place="margin">See Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Trent.</hi> Book 2. <hi>Pag.</hi> 252. and 216. <hi>Non ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis de paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendagre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, Cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant qua ſutor de orando. Calvin Inſtit.</hi> 4. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>Sect.</hi> 12, 13 Jer. 23. 13 14. Ezek. 22. 26. Zach. 11. 17.</note>. They <hi>ſay</hi> they are men of GOD; wee <hi>ſee</hi> they are men of the world. They <hi>ſay</hi> they ſtand for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> wee <hi>ſee</hi> they ſtand againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> oppoſing Him in all His wayes. They <hi>ſay</hi> they are Miniſters of the Goſpel; wee <hi>ſee</hi> folly is in them, and horrible things are committed by them. They <hi>ſay</hi> they are Shep-heards; wee <hi>ſee</hi> they are Idoll-Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, and the ſword is upon their right eye, and arme; their Arme is cleane dried-up, and their right eye is utterly darkened: This wee <hi>ſee,</hi> that they are not what they <hi>ſay</hi> they are. Their mouth was yet wider open to utter blaſphemies; for</p>
               <p>2. They ſaid they were Biſhops by <hi>divine Right:</hi> I mean it not in their ſenſe now, nor as it was commonly underſtood, though that was an high preſumption, this was more. They ſaid they were Biſhops, and would have made themſelves ſo, by the ſame right, whereby the Lord Chriſt, <hi>bleſſed for ever,</hi> was made a Prieſt <hi>for ever;</hi> By the ſame right would they have made themſelves, Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Arch-Deacons, &amp;c. <hi>for ever.</hi> Marke wee whether it was not juſt ſo; To be eſtabliſhed by an <hi>Oath,</hi> was a peculiar Inſtalment to our <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> the great Biſhop of our ſoules, He <hi>was made with an Oath;</hi> Other Prieſts, <hi>without an Oath</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 7. 20, 21.</note>; But ſo they thought to eſtabliſh themſelves, that their thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> might endure <hi>for ever;</hi> for, unto an immutable thing, wherein it was impoſſible (they thought) to be miſtaken, they had fixed the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor of their hope, both ſure and ſtedfaſt. What doe you thinke of this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke it to be a greater blaſphemy, than the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:154605:7"/>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>It is hard to make a compariſon, who blaſphemes moſt; he, that blaſphemes in words; or he, that blaſphemes in deed. But you thinke this to be a great blaſphemy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Surely you cannot thinke leſſe, for here they ſaid more preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, than that proud King did; <q>Wee <hi>will</hi> exalt our Throne above <note place="margin">Iſa. 14. 13, 14.</note> the Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>res of GOD; wee <hi>will aſcend above the height of the Clouds;</hi> wee <hi>will</hi> be <hi>like the moſt High, (will</hi> was all their reaſon.)</q> And now ſee what the LORD has don! (for it is the worke of His hands) He <hi>has brought them downe even to the ſides of the pit.</hi> I argue from hence, the lawfulneſſe of the eradicating, or rooting-out this abominable roote (the Hierarchy with its branches) by the ſame Argument, which they uſed for the <hi>rooting</hi> themſelves-in; And we are ſure, that there is ſtrength enough in the Argument, if the higheſt preſumption, and moſt horrid blaſphemy can give ſtrength unto it, for all this is in it.</p>
               <p>Hitherto wee have ſeene the <hi>Law</hi> and Hand of the LORD againſt theſe men, for the Abomination committed againſt the LORDS day. 2. For their preſumptuons <hi>ſayings</hi> and blaſphemous <hi>doings</hi> againſt the LORD Himſelfe. Wee proceed now to another Argument, for the Caſting of them forth, becauſe of their <hi>force</hi> and <hi>fraud</hi> againſt the people of GOD, the <hi>Clergie</hi> indeed, the <hi>lot</hi> of His Inheritance; Thus I argue;</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>III</label> They that did call the people to the Sacrifices of ſtrange gods; They that did ſeeke to <hi>entice</hi> and <hi>turne-away</hi> the ſervants of GOD from ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo good a <hi>Maſter,</hi> were, by GODS command, to be <hi>hanged-up</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Num. 25. 4.</note> before the LORD;</q> The Biſhops have ſpoken all that they could ſpeake, and have don all that they could doe, whereby to <hi>entice</hi> and <note place="margin">Deut. 13. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>thruſt-away</hi> the people of <hi>God,</hi> from the ſervice of <hi>God,</hi> to ſerve abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idolls, the worke of mens hands; Therefore, by mans law, theſe are to be Caſt-out; What will you deny here?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>This, That the Biſhops have don as you have ſaid, ſought to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice</hi> the people of <hi>God</hi> ſecretly, &amp; by <hi>fraud:</hi> or by <hi>force</hi> to <hi>thruſt</hi> his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple away from the ſervice of their <hi>God;</hi> All this I deny.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>All this you deny! It is quickly ſaid, but you ſtand charged to conſider, what you <hi>deny,</hi> leaſt you contradict the <hi>evidence</hi> and <hi>verdict</hi> which all your ſenſes give-in unto you touching this matter; I ſhall call them-in now to give witneſſe; and I charge you before the <hi>Living God,</hi> anſwer now the truth, and the whole truth, as your ſenſes have made report unto you; firſt,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>What <hi>heare</hi> you from their Pulpits?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot anſwer that queſtion; for the Arch-biſhops have not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154605:8"/> preached theſe (I know not how) many yeeres: and the Biſhope preach in the <hi>Lent-time</hi> onely; and then there is ſuch a throng to heare a Biſhop preach, that I cannot come within hearing; Therefore I can give you no certaine report.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Though you heard not the Biſhop, yet you heard of his Sermon; What heard you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>That the Biſhop no ſooner named his text, but he ran away from it as from an adverſary, with which he could not agree: Indeed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Biſhops Sermon is very various, and monſtrous, ſo inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent it is with its ſelfe, and with the text: for though the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be conſtant to its ſelfe, yet the Biſhop and his Chaplin (for he ſtood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up often in the Biſhops place) did mould, frame, and faſhion his Text as you can doe Waxe, to the faſhion of the time, or buſineſſe in hand, ſtill turning head upon <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Word,</hi> and preaching not the <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which God ſaid unto him,</hi> but what beſt agreed with the work in hand, <note place="margin">Jonah 3. 2.</note> to <hi>make the King abſolute;</hi> and <hi>the Biſhop an abſolute Monarch alſo.</hi> So they preached; for juſt as the time ſerved, ſo the text ſhould ſerve. Now he preached-up the Kings Prerogative; and preached downe the Subjects Priviledge; ſet the Kings throne above GODS throne, and his people below his foote. This was the chiefe part of the Sermon, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to the Deſigne in hand, as it was croſſe to the text. Then <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy</hi> muſt be <hi>Aſſerted</hi> by <hi>Divine Right;</hi> The Government in the Church muſt be Monarchicall, as in the Civill ſtate, it muſt be abſolute: And the better to bring about all this, They preached-up <hi>Ceremonies, Altars,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">A brutiſh ſervice wil render a people brutiſh.</note> and <hi>Organs;</hi> and the lawfulneſſe of the warre with <hi>Scotland;</hi> the purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that brother with a ſword; <hi>Peace with Rome,</hi> but no peace with <hi>Scotland;</hi> What ever was the Text, that was the Doctrine and ſubject matter a great while. I pray you doe not aske mee any further account of the Biſhops Sermon; I can give no more account of it, than the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man can of his dreames. Surely, It was ſo <hi>Heterogeneous,</hi> incongruous, Inconſiſtent with, I ſay not <hi>baptized Reaſon,</hi> but common reaſon, and <note place="margin">Baptiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> ſenſe, that in very truth, no good report can be made thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I beleeve you, and therefore I have done with your <hi>eare:</hi> What reade you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>A very godly booke, the Arch-biſhops againſt the <hi>Jeſuit Fiſher;</hi> wherein there is nothing ſure to <hi>thruſt</hi> away the people of GOD from the ſervice of GOD: but rather from the ſervice of <hi>Rome;</hi> I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Be not ſo confident of an Arch-biſhops booke; for, as one ſaid of his loving friend, a <hi>blow from that hand would never hurt him:</hi> So you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154605:8"/> may be confident, That the Arch-biſhop never intended, by that booke, to hurt the Pope, or his Cauſe, but to promote it heartily: I doe aſſure you, that the Arch-biſhops intent was ſo honeſt, ſo true, ſo heartie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo falſe toward the true Church, that had he had as many necks, as I reade one man had mouthes (no fewer than fiftie,) they deſerve every one to be tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſed up about with a rope; and yet not a full recompence of reward for his ungodly labour in that booke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Proceed, What reade you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>A very pious booke, which has thruſt us quite off from <hi>Rome;</hi> has cauſed a <hi>deadly fewd</hi> betwixt us and <hi>Rome,</hi> it is called, <hi>No peace with Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>There is ſuch a book indeed, but you do reade alſo, that the ſame man has written, <hi>That Rome is a true Church;</hi> have you not read ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and truly, me thought, there was a great contrarietie in words, ſuch a difference as could never be <hi>reconciled; No peace with Rome,</hi> yet <hi>Rome a true Church,</hi> it can never be <hi>reconciled,</hi> thought I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, that it can, though not well; diſtinguiſh the times, and perſons, and all is <hi>reconciled;</hi> The ſame man writ both, <hi>No peace with Rome</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was Biſhop: <hi>Rome, a true Church,</hi> after he was Biſhop; The one, as a Miniſter of Chriſt, the other, as a Miniſter of Antichriſt. When he was a Biſhop, he muſt write as a Biſhop, that is the point. And he could <hi>reconcile</hi> all very well (he had been unbiſhopt elſe) and ſo he put forth a book, and called it a <hi>Reconciler;</hi> which cauſed more than a ſuſpition of the man, that he was not a fearfull man onely, but a <hi>right man,</hi> a <hi>Proctor for Rome,</hi> a ſubtill broker for <hi>Babylon.</hi> GOD give him an heart to think of this, for ſurely, ſuch a man as he ſhould not have given ſo juſt a cauſe of ſuſpition. But proceed; What reade you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Pray you doe not trouble me with that queſtion any more, let it ſuffice to tell you, what I know in two words, the Biſhops books, and books licenced by their Chaplines (if they may be called books) are very many, and ſtand as fully charged againſt their LORD, and the <hi>Lords Anoynted,</hi> as any books in <hi>Italy,</hi> or in the Popes Library can doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Ile aske you no more, <hi>What you reade;</hi> but what doe you <hi>ſee;</hi> doe you ſee any thing from the Biſhops tending to edification?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, if <hi>edification</hi> be a <hi>building</hi> and <hi>ſetting-up,</hi> (as I thinke the word doth import) I ſee much tending that way. I ſaw Biſhop <hi>Wrens</hi> Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opened, where I ſaw (what doe you call them?) pretty knacks, Images and Crucifixes, &amp;c. All tending to <hi>edification</hi> of <hi>Romes</hi> Church, and the Popes leige people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Have you ſeene any <hi>Altars?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:154605:9"/>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>You might as well aske mee, whether I have ſeene any <hi>Churcheſ,</hi> or <hi>Chappels,</hi> or <hi>Cathedralls;</hi> for in every of theſe places, there is an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> and moſt eminently ſeene there; there is an <hi>aſcent</hi> to it, by degrees and ſteps, as to <hi>Solomons</hi> Throne; Indeed I may anſwer your queſtion in the words of the LORD, <hi>According to the number of (Thy Cities)</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 2.</note> of thy <hi>Cathedralls,</hi> thy <hi>Chancells,</hi> thy <hi>Chappels, are thy Altars, thy gods, O England.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You have bolted out a Truth here, I thinke, before you were aware; I pray you, let us underſtand our ſelves, and examine whether you have ſpoke a Truth or no? I asked you, whether you have ſeene any <hi>Altars?</hi> You anſwer mee, <hi>Yes,</hi> as many as there be <hi>Cathedralls,</hi> and <hi>Chapp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lls,</hi> and then you called them <hi>gods:</hi> I pray you underſtand, that it is not the Biſhops calling <hi>wood</hi> or <hi>ſtone,</hi> an <hi>Altar,</hi> or the ſetting of it like a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſer-board in your Kitchin, <hi>Altarwiſe,</hi> which makes it an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar?</hi> No: They may (for they are B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhops, you may not) take a ſtone a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a ſtock, hew and poliſh the ſame, then <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aviſh gold</hi> out <hi>of the bagg,</hi> and ſo adorne it: though all this coſt and paines be beſtowed upon it, yet it is not an <hi>Altar,</hi> nor a <hi>god</hi> yet; no nor yet, when they have ſet-it-up, as was ſaid, <hi>Altar-wiſe,</hi> like the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſer table in your Kitchin, yet it is not an <hi>Altar,</hi> nor a <hi>god</hi> yet. But if the <hi>great man</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 2. 9.</note>, the Arch-biſhop hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth himſelfe; and the <hi>meane man,</hi> the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eriour Biſhop, <hi>bowech-downe</hi> before it, then you may call it an <hi>Altar,</hi> and, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you pleaſe, a <hi>god</hi> too. But if you have ſeene no <hi>bending</hi> nor <hi>cringing,</hi> nor <hi>bowing,</hi> nor <hi>humbling</hi> before this <hi>wood</hi> and <hi>ſtone,</hi> then you have miſcalled this <hi>wood</hi> and <hi>ſtone,</hi> and wronged the Arch-biſhops and Biſhops all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I have not miſcalled it; I have called it as they have named it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You are a man of ſhort Diſcourſe, pray you remember what was ſaid; That it is not the forme, faſhion, placing, ſetling of <hi>wood</hi> or <hi>ſtons,</hi> or calling it an <hi>Altar,</hi> which makes it an <hi>Altar:</hi> none of all this; but the <hi>bowing</hi> and <hi>humbling,</hi> that gives unto it a worſhip, and that makes it an <hi>Altar,</hi> and a <hi>god</hi> hoth <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecce plumbatur erig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tur nec adhuc Deus eſt. Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur oratur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unc po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtremo Deus eſt. M. Fel. in fol.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 16. <hi>lin.</hi> 27.</note>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>But now, nor Pope, nor Biſhop, will grant, That <hi>bowing</hi> and <hi>humbling</hi> before <hi>wood</hi> and <hi>ſtone,</hi> make it a <hi>god.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke as you ſay, and no matter what Pope, or Biſhop, Jeſuit, or Papiſt, grant ordeny. This wee affirme to the face of all the Papiſts in the world; That this <hi>bowing</hi> and <hi>humbling</hi> (no Civill worſhip in the Church) is a worſhip proper and peculiar to God alone; He is a God, whom wee ſo worſhip; or wee make it, though out <hi>wood</hi> or <hi>ſtone,</hi> wee make it a <hi>god,</hi> as much as in us lies; while wee make <hi>wood</hi> and <hi>ſtone</hi> ſhare in this <hi>worſhip,</hi> wee deifie it, wee exalt it on high, (and our folly with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154605:9"/> it) wee make it more than a creature. In a word, By <hi>bowing</hi> and <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling</hi> before wood and ſtone, wee make it a falſe <hi>god,</hi> and our ſelves; I ſay not, abominable; but a very abomination. My Queſtion then is; Have you ſeene any of all this, <hi>bowing</hi> and <hi>humbling</hi> before wood and ſtone? Have you ſeene Arch-biſhops and Biſhops, the <hi>great men,</hi> and the <hi>meane men</hi> doe ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I can give you a cleare anſwer to your Queſtion; for I can tell you, what I have ſeene with mine eyes. In <hi>Aprill</hi> 1640. The day after the Parliament ſate, then and there, in <hi>Pauls</hi> Quire, I obſerved the Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops every one, except two, ducking ſo low before the Altar, that their back-parts appeared, and their fore-parts (their heads) diſ-appeared: And what call you that? <hi>Bowing</hi> and <hi>humbling</hi> ſure. And what they did in <hi>Pauls,</hi> they would doe in the Kings, and Queens Chappell, and in their owne, where they have the ſame <hi>piles</hi> of wood and ſtone, with wax-tapers upon them; and Prieſts (with what call you it upon their backs?) before the Altar; I call it an Altar now by your allowance, and a <hi>god</hi> too; for the <hi>great man</hi> has humbled himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, and the <hi>meane man</hi> has bowed downe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Had wee time to ſtay upon it, I would bid you reade on; <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forgive them not;</hi> Theſe are terrible words, but wee muſt paſſe them over, and ſo proceed, Your eye has don you good ſervice; It has ſhowne you the moſt abominable Idolatry that ever was committed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sunne, exceeding that of the Prieſts in the Queens Chappell; for there they <hi>humble</hi> themſelves, and <hi>bow,</hi> but not before wood and ſtone, but before a <hi>wooden</hi> or a <hi>Breaden-god,</hi> the worke of their owne hands. They that can make gods with their owne hands, can worſhip them, and with the ſame Reaſon. I deſcend now from the eye, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of your other ſenſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>What did you <hi>Smell,</hi> and <hi>Taſte</hi> all the time of the Biſhops raigne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>As was the ſmell of the Services in the Queens Chappell; where was the groſſeſt, the rankeſt, the moſt ſtinking Popery; yet not ſo abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, as the Biſhops Idolatry, for the Reaſon above-ſaid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>What have you <hi>felt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhould not aske me that Queſtion; I am, as they call mee, <hi>a lay-man</hi> (by which name, I cannot tell my ſelfe what I am) nor muſt you aske any of the Biſhops Clergy-men [The Biſhops and their <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> are the <hi>lot</hi> and <hi>inheritance</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> the <hi>Clergy,</hi> they ſay, though] They are as their Lords are; Aske a Miniſter of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> any one faithfull Steward in Gods houſe, he will tell you, That if the Biſhops could not <hi>thrust</hi> him off from the worke and ſervice of the LORD,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154605:10"/> then he could <hi>thruſt</hi> him-out of GODS houſe, and his owne; and <hi>thruſt</hi> yet ſorer at him, till he had <hi>thruſt</hi> him out of the Land; It is unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble what Gods faithfull Miniſters, and faithfull people, have ſuffered from the Biſhops themſelves, and their bloudy ſervants; what Devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring words! what violence from their hands!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Very well: Now I pray you anſwer mee from what all your <hi>ſenſes</hi> have reported to you, whether you have obſerved any thing ſpoken or don by the Biſhops, any <hi>fraud,</hi> any <hi>force,</hi> whereby to <hi>thruſt</hi> away the people of GOD from the ſervice of GOD, their good <hi>Maſter</hi> in <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</hi> Anſwer according to the report your <hi>ſenſes</hi> have given to your underſtanding touching this matter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>That the Biſhops have <hi>endeavoured</hi> by all their ſayings and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, To render The <hi>Lords</hi> Day, <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>contemptible;</hi> more <hi>marred</hi> than any Day. They <hi>endeavoured</hi> alſo, to <hi>thruſt</hi> away King and people from the worſhip and ſervice of their <hi>God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>That is enough, for grant ſo much (and yet more you muſt grant) and then that followes, which, being well proſecuted, will ſtrike at the Biſhops heads, and truſſe them ſhort by the necks. But yet you muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer mee more fully, and ſo you will put me to the trouble of other Queſtions, and your ſelfe to the anſwers. Was all this <hi>fraud</hi> and <hi>force,</hi> theſe <hi>Devices, Methods, Depths</hi> of the Biſhops, were all theſe but an <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour</hi> onely, and a Deſigne with them? <q>In <hi>polluting To pollute The Lords Day;</hi> In <hi>defiling To Defile the houſe of God, and the ſervices there;</hi> Was it but an <hi>endeavour</hi> only to <hi>thruſt</hi> away the <hi>Deputy from the faith?</hi> To ſtop the mouthes of the Miniſters? To <hi>thruſt</hi> them out of GODS houſe, and their owne, and into priſons, or out of the Land? Was it but an <hi>endeavour;</hi> but a Deſigne onely, To make ſome of them, who would doe their dutie, <hi>a ſpectacle to God, Angells, and men?</hi>
                  </q> [I know the <hi>Lord</hi> has His <hi>Reſerve,</hi> a <hi>Remnant, a few Names,</hi> who would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file their garments; He did preſerve ſome out of the fire; and ſome in the fire; ſome He delivered from the Lions den; and ſome He reſcued from out of the Lions mouth. I know the LORD has had His <hi>Reſerves</hi> evermore; and His <hi>Deliverances,</hi> and His <hi>Reſcues</hi> are wonderfull. It is granted alſo, That all theſe <hi>hard words</hi> and <hi>ungodly deeds,</hi> have tended to the ſpreading of the Goſpel; the furtherance of it even in this Land, and to the encreaſe of the faithfull, the <hi>ennobling</hi> and <hi>hightening</hi> of their Spirits, by the oppoſition made againſt them: It has made many <hi>lights</hi> burne the brighter, the ſtronger the winde was to put them out. The LORD has many and faire wayes to <hi>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rute</hi> His Nobles, and Worthies, wayes well beſeeming and becomming the <hi>God</hi> of Gods, and <hi>Lord</hi> of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154605:10"/> Lords. But what the <hi>Lord</hi> has don, what good He has brought out of all this evill, is not the Queſtion now.] I charge you before the <hi>Living God,</hi> anſwer me to this; Were all the writings, ſayings, doings of the Biſhops, but an <hi>endeavour</hi> onely, but a Deſigne? Have they effected no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing touching the premiſſes: Open your mouth, and ſpeak as the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of God, and as in the eares of God, Have the Biſhops but <hi>endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> onely in polluting <hi>To pollute The Lords Day?</hi> Anſwer me that firſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>It cannot be denied, That the Biſhops ſet-out a Book, wherein they gave an <hi>Advouſion</hi> of libertie to the people, for <hi>harmleſſe ſports,</hi> and <hi>paſs-times,</hi> to paſſe over the <hi>Sunday,</hi> as they, The <hi>Lords day,</hi> as yee call it. Indeed this <hi>Grant of libertie,</hi> workt contrary effects, as all men ſay, but that was by <hi>accident,</hi> as the <hi>Logicians</hi> ſay; It was not in the nature of the thing, but in the nature of the people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You are miſtaken in the firſt word, and ſo all along. You call the <hi>Declaration</hi> for <hi>Sports,</hi> a <hi>grant of libertie</hi> to the people. That is true, though they need not ſuch a <hi>grant,</hi> for they will take it without leave; But it was a <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Command</hi> to the <hi>Paſtours,</hi> To give their people that libertie. Secondly, You call them <hi>harmleſſe Sports,</hi> and <hi>lawfull paſs-times.</hi> You ſhould underſtand, That theſe very names, <hi>ſports</hi> and <hi>paſs-times,</hi> are not compatible, not any way congruous with ſo ſacred a Time, as is The <hi>Lords Day:</hi> Therefore the Biſhops ſhould not have diſtinguiſhed of <hi>ſports,</hi> but have caſt-them-out, as neither <hi>Civill,</hi> nor <hi>Harm-leſſe</hi> nor <hi>Man-like;</hi> but the contrary: nor <hi>lawfull</hi> (ſpecially mixt dancing) on any day, moſt unlawfull and brutiſh on the <hi>Lords Day.</hi> Thirdly, You ſay, That this Declaration for Sports, worke contrary to the Biſhops meaning; and that the effects were by <hi>accident.</hi> Wee ſay the Declaration workt according to the heart of the Biſhop, And that ſuch effects, as wee have now ſeene, were in the nature of the thing; as well as in the nature of the people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt remember, That there were two very godly expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Declaration for Sports, whereby the Biſhops did declare a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pious meaning ſure. The firſt; <hi>That they commanded no other ſports, but what would make the people fit for warre,</hi> that is the expreſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>A godly expreſſion ſaid you, and declaring a godly intent! by giving the people a libertie to <hi>ſport</hi> and <hi>paſſe-away</hi> a ſacred Time, with <hi>Whitſon-Ales, May-games,</hi> &amp;c. thereby to make the people <hi>fit for warre!</hi> Ile tell you a Story, whereby you ſhall be inabled to give Judgement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this. <hi>Cyrus,</hi> a brave Commander, vexed ſtill with the <hi>Lydians,</hi> a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry warlike people, bethought himſelfe of a way to tame the <hi>Lydians,</hi> and to make them <hi>ſober men,</hi> by making them firſt <hi>drunke</hi> with wine, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154605:11"/> ſotted with pleaſures; for thus it was; <q>
                     <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſets forth a gracious Declaration unto them; gave the <hi>Lydians</hi> the ſame libertie then, which the Biſhops gave to the people now, A <hi>licence</hi> to ſet-up Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes; <note place="margin">Cauponias <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t ludicras artes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercere.</note> To exerciſe their bodies, and refreſh their minds with ſports, paſs-times, games, &amp;c.</q> I put a Queſtion now, and crave your anſwer; Was <hi>Cyrus</hi> his intent, by this grant of libertie unto the <hi>Lydians,</hi> To make them <hi>fit</hi> or <hi>unfit for warre?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Unfit ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You have ſpoken like a man, the very Truth, for ſo it was; A ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry warlike people before, becomes as weake as water preſently after; And, to give you in ſhort, what <hi>Aelian</hi> contributes to this Story; Theſe people were ſo delighted in dauncing, That they taught their horſes to daunce: So when the horſes heard the <hi>Trumpet</hi> and the <hi>Drum,</hi> they thought it was the <hi>Taber</hi> and the <hi>Pipe,</hi> ſo the horſes fell to daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and gave up their Riders to the ſpoile. And now if you cannot, the preſent time ſhall declare the Biſhops meaning, and the purpoſe of thoſe words; <hi>To make the people fit for warre; (i. e.)</hi> make a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fit for deſtruction, To be devoured by the mouth of the ſword, as it is at this Day. The people were made drunke with wine, and ſtrong drinke, and drunke with pleaſure, Now the <hi>Lord</hi> has made them drunke with their owne bloud in their owne Land. Wee, by command from the Biſhops, have blaſphemed Gods Name; polluted His day; defiled His Sanctuaries; Now The LORD has made us <hi>fit for warre</hi> Now He has given us <hi>for a ſpoile,</hi> and <hi>to the Robbers, He has powered upon us the fury of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa 42. ω.</note> 
                  <hi>His anger, and the ſtrength of Battle.</hi> And doe wee complaine, That our Cities are, ſome of them, waſted, and otherſome, impoveriſhed? Let us admire, That our Cities are not all ſo waſted, and left without Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants; That all are not made as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and like unto <hi>Gomoral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> That is the wonder, and the patience of a <hi>God!</hi> That a <hi>God,</hi> ſo provoked, ſhould be ſo gracious, there is matter for wonder.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>To interrupt you a little, I muſt tell you, That the Declaration for ſports and Paſs-times, do's declare its ſelfe againſt <hi>ſilthy Tiplings</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſſe,</hi> The other expreſſion, very godly and gracious! expreſſe againſt <hi>Tipling,</hi> that ſwiniſh ſinne, forbidding it in expreſſe tearmes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You are miſtaken; That <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>claration</hi> commands Riott, Luxury, Drunkenneſſe. Intemperance, and wantonneſſe, Though not directly, and in expreſſe words, yet by moſt neceſſary &amp; undoubted conſequence, as an effect from the cauſe, which being naturall and ſufficient, inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the effect, and alwayes giveth it. It is true, There was an expreſſe forbidding of <hi>filthy Tiplings,</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſſe,</hi> for ſo run the words;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154605:11"/> They are but words; <hi>Filthy Tiplings,</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Rioting in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 13</note> 
                  <hi>the day time,</hi> all theſe were in that Charter for libertie, as in the roote; As Death was in the Pott; As a fall in pride; As deſtruction and death, in ſin and rebellion. It is not poſſible to countenance <hi>Whitſun-Ales,</hi> and diſcountenance <hi>Drunkenneſſe;</hi> To Command <hi>Wakes,</hi> and forbid <hi>Tiplings;</hi> To allow of ſetting-up <hi>May-poles,</hi> and other ſports therwith uſed, and diſallow of <hi>Chambering</hi> and <hi>Wantonneſſe.</hi> If I grant the cauſe, I cannot forbid the effect, no more than I can forbid a ſtone to fall down-ward, or an Eagle to haſten to its prey; no more than I can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the fire to burne, or the Sun to ſhine. But if I take away the fuell, then the fire will goe out. No man will ſhow himſelfe ſo uncivill, and below himſelfe, as to Command Drunkenneſſe, Intemperance, wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in plaine tearmes; Nor need wee a command to doe that, wherein our natures too much command us; Where the law of nature ſpeakes, no need it ſhould be aſſiſted by a Commandement; Wee carry about us a law in our members, which leads us captive to the law of ſin. If a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate will be entreated for the erecting &amp; ſupporting of bloudy dens, <hi>Schooles</hi> of <hi>miſ-rule,</hi> nurceries of the Gallowes (ſo bleſſed <hi>Bolton</hi> calls Ale-houſes) he doth encourage and ſupport ſwiniſh Drunkards, worſe than ſwine in the Church, and more harmfull than they in that garden; Set open the Ale-houſe, you may be ſure ſome body will come reeling out. The ſame may be ſaid of ſetting up <hi>May-poles,</hi> and countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing other ſports thereto belonging; You cannot command them, and forbid the taking pleaſure to <hi>riott in the day time.</hi> Wee doe not reade, (and it is worth our obſervation) that <hi>Balaam</hi> did command the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to commit whoredome with the daughters of <hi>Moah.</hi> He did not point <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to goe to the Tent in the face of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and on that ſolemn day; he had more civilitie than ſo. <hi>Balaam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 24. 14. Chap. 31. 16. See <hi>Trem.</hi>
                  </note> did adviſe, onely ſo and no more. <hi>Balaam</hi> was an old Man; as he was, ſo his counſell muſt be, <hi>grave,</hi> not ſeemingly ſowre, nor apparently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civill. Let <hi>Iſra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi> and <hi>Moab</hi> come to an <hi>inter-view;</hi> let them ſee each others faces; let them be preſent at each others ſacrifices. This was the Counſell, but worſe than a curſe, for now folly will be committed in <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi> no doubt of that: And then The GOD of <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be offended wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h <hi>Iſrael</hi> He will depart, and then a curſe followes, as certain as when the Cloud is thicke, The thunder-clap followes (in our ſenſes) the ſparkling flaſh; Bad Counſell is worſe than <hi>ſower</hi> Counſell, and more poyſon u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, for by bad counſell, not ſower counſell, <hi>Balaam taught Balack To lay a ſtumbling block before Iſrael,</hi> as the Spirit calleth <note n="a" place="margin">Rev. 2. 14</note> it: And it proved in the iſſue <hi>ſower</hi> counſell too; <hi>Iſrael</hi> found it ſo, as wee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154605:12"/> reade <note n="b" place="margin">Numb. 25. 9. 1 Cor. 10. 8</note>. To apply here; The Biſhops did not command Idolatry, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Goe ſerve other gods.</hi> No, but they ſet-up Altars, That was enough to defile the whole Land, and to make a people commit <hi>adultery with ſtones and with ſtocks</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Jer. 3. 9.</note>. The Biſhops did not command <hi>Tipling and Drunkenneſſe.</hi> No; But they commanded <hi>ſports</hi> and <hi>paſs-times, Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon-Ales,</hi> and <hi>May-poles;</hi> Allow the cauſe, and countenance that, you allow the effect, and countenance that alſo which naturally iſſueth thence. If the maid lay leaven in three pecks of meale, ſhee need not command it to ſower the whole lumpe; Put fire and fuell together, you need not bid it to burne; Set a deſirable object before the eye, you need not command the heart to luſt after it; Set the windowes, doores, gates all open, you need not bid the enemy enter; A ſmall ſparke falling into gunpowder, you know what it will doe, whether you will or no, or though you command the contrary. And you know as well, That they, who command <hi>Wakes, Whitſon-Ales,</hi> ſetting up <hi>May-poles,</hi> and other ſports therewith uſed, do command filthy Tiplings, and Drunkenneſſe, and other abuſes in ſuch diſtempers uſuall. I have been the longer upon this, to cleare your judgement in ſo neceſſary a point. I proceed now to the next Queſtion; Did the Biſhops but <hi>endeavour,</hi> was it but their <hi>ſeeking</hi> onely, To <hi>turne the Deputy from the faith?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. 13. 8.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot make anſwere here, for I cannot tell whoſe endeavour, and ſeeking it was; I can tell All are turned from the Faith, King and Biſhop, Prieſt and people, and all; All are turnd away from <hi>God,</hi> that is cleare enough. The <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> are turned <hi>up-ſide downe,</hi> what poſſibly Church-men could doe, But who was the chiefeſt Artiſt, and Turner here, that I cannot ſo well tell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>If you cannot, you are content to be informed at this point from them who can tell us from ancient Records, That <hi>the Biſhop turned the Deputy from the faith,</hi> and with him very much people; wee will reade the Records; but conſider with mee firſt, How high the Biſhops Power and Authoritie was?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>How high the Biſhops Power? He was not in the <hi>Zenith</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">The <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith</hi> is the higheſt point in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens over your head: The <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar</hi> is that point of earth your foot ſtands upon; The place wher the Popes muſt be laid, and their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in the Duſt.</note> of the Church, for there onely the Pope ſits. Take it at the height of its eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, The Biſhops power was but Derivative, as a ſtreame from the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> a baſtard-power from the Pope.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You are miſtaken, our Biſhops power was as independant as the Popes power is; as abſolute a Pope in his Dioceſſe (and that was all over the Land) as the Pope is all over the Chriſtian world: And all his Actions, Dictates, Determinations, &amp;c. were as <hi>Magiſteriall</hi> and Pope-like, as ever were the Biſhops in <hi>Rome.</hi> But I pray you conſider with mee, what I was about to ſay, but that you interrupted mee.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:154605:12"/>
               <p> 2. What an influence (like ſome malignant Starr) the Biſhops power had, from the Councell-Table, Starr-chamber, every Court and place, into the affaires and tranſactions of Church and State.</p>
               <p>3. Enquire wee of ancient dayes, and wee ſhall well underſtand, That, while the Prieſts were good, The King was good: When the people might ſay, <hi>He is a very good Prieſt;</hi> Then they might ſay, <hi>He is a very good King. Jehojada</hi> an excellent Prieſt, for he made a Covenant <hi>between</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 23. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>People;</hi> That all ſhould be, not their owne, but <hi>The</hi> LORDS <hi>People;</hi> an excellent Prieſt he. So was <hi>Joaſh</hi> the King, as forward and zealous (to ſay no more) as the Prieſt was <note n="*" place="margin">Ver. 6.</note>. The Prieſts zeale kindled the Kings zeale, made it <hi>fervent</hi> and boyling-hott; So it was like the burning of thornes, quickly in a flame, and as quickly out; It was not a zeale, a fire from above; But this is the point; So long as the Prieſt was excellently good, a living example before the Kings eye, ſo long the King was good. <hi>Zechariah,</hi> a very good Prieſt too, And <hi>in his dayes, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah was a very good King,</hi> for he <hi>ſought God in the dayes of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Chro. 26</note> 
                  <hi>Zechariah:</hi> and all that while <hi>he proſpered:</hi> I might be large, wee will reade but one or two Records more; The one tells us;</p>
               <p>4. That the Temple, and the Temple-worke there, was never defiled, while the chiefe Prieſts there did their office. It is true, The King fretted againſt the Prieſts, and ſtormed againſt the LORD, till the LORD <note place="margin">2 Chron. 26. 20.</note> ſmote him in his forehead, then he was calme and ſtill; But while the chiefe Prieſt, and foureſcore more with him, did their office, all was well, except the King; It was ill with him, who did fret againſt the Prieſts, becauſe they did their office, and againſt The <hi>Lord,</hi> That char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them ſo; It was ill with him. But the <hi>Cenſer</hi> and the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> was in their hands, unto whom it did belong, To offer unto the LORD, and ſerve before Him. Let us record one example more, and that will relate to theſe times. King <hi>Ahaz</hi> had a ſervant, <hi>a Right man</hi> for his ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vice; But as vile a Prieſt as was in all <hi>Judah;</hi> What was the King? If any man makes it a queſtion, The ſacred Records will reſolve him, As miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a King, as his Idolatries, &amp; other abominations could make him: And his Prieſt, the baſeſt ſervant in the world, a ſlave to his Maſters luſts, and his own; The Prieſt haſtened his Maſters deſtruction, <hi>for he did, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings 16. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>to all that King A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>az Commanded;</hi> I have read the Records What is the reſult from thence? You muſt tell us; for from the premiſſes, you have drawne the Conclu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion; I pray you what is it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>That, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it be now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as in ancient dayes it has been, then the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop is the <hi>Witch,</hi> the <hi>Sorcerer,</hi> he is the cun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing Artiſt, he turnes all up-ſide downe, he has turned the King, and people from the faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:154605:13"/>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>There is no new thing under the Sun, What was, now is; like Prieſts, like people; Brutiſh Prieſts, brutiſh people. And now ſith you have anſwered mee ſo clearely to this, Ile aske you no more queſtions; I will not aske you whether the Biſhops <hi>endeavoured</hi> onely To defile the houſe of GOD, and the ſervices there? Not; whether they ſet-up <hi>their Threſholds, by Gods Threſholds</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ezech. 43. 8. <hi>Adhiben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones ſuas ad praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta mea.</hi> Jun.</note>? Not, whether they thruſt GOD out of His Houſe, and His ſervants out of their houſes, and <hi>Gods</hi> Houſe alſo? Not, whether they have thruſt His ſervants into corners, and out of the Land? Not, whether they have uſed <hi>Gods</hi> precious ones, villanouſly? All this is as cleare to all the Chriſtian world, as is the noone day: And indeed, you have yeelded to all this, when you granted, what you could not deny, That the Biſhops <hi>ſet-up Altars,</hi> and <hi>made gods.</hi> Will the GOD of gods endure this, To be mated in His owne houſe with gods of mans owne making? Surely, ſurely, This is enough to cauſe the LORD to meaſure us, as He did <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael;</hi> or (to relate unto Times nearer hand) to <hi>ſtreteh over this Land alſo, the line of Germany,</hi> and the <hi>Plummet of the Palatinate-houſe,</hi> To cauſe <hi>the Land to be wiped,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 21. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>as a man wipeth a diſh, wiping it and turning it upſide-downe;</hi> Enough and enough, (ſo much as a man can doe, and was in his power) To make all the Inhabitants of the Land <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts</hi> all; Setting-up Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and making of gods, has don all this; O wonderfull! That all this has been don here before the face of His Holineſſe, and yet He has ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, He has not meated out unto us, as unto other Lands; He has not wiped the Land yet as a maid wipeth a diſh; He has not made our Land <hi>Hormah</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 21. 3.</note>, utter Deſtruction, or <hi>Anathema,</hi> a curſe; Not yet, Though theſe abominations are found here; And yet behold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greater Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation than has been ſhewen hitherto, which I ſhall not declare here.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you let us heare all; declare what you can declare; ſhew me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d the world, that other Abomination.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt ſpare mee, and your ſelfe that trouble; Indeed I can ſay nothing touching the Biſhops <hi>example,</hi> that is the abomination, my words cannot reach unto it; how provoaking! how defiling! how cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting! how ſpreading! No leproſie ſo infecting, ſo deſtroying. This <hi>how</hi> cannot be expreſſed; A Biſhops Example! A Biſhop, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up Altars! A Biſhop, and make gods! Ah LORD, how many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand thouſand ſoules, has a Biſhops example Deſtroyed! He has by his abominable Doctrines (as wee heard,) he has <hi>thruſt</hi> away King and people from the worſhip of their GOD; By his <hi>example,</hi> he has <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det lingua jubet vita</hi> Athan.</note>, <hi>forced</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 2. 14 <hi>Cogi eos dicit, qui exemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o Petri, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daizabant</hi> Jun.</note>. <hi>compelled</hi> King and people to ſerve other gods. I can ſay nothing touching this <hi>Abomination;</hi> I confeſſe it is hard to forbeare;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154605:13"/> but I doe forbeare, for your ſake, That you may now take the more ſcope, and libertie, to ſay what you have to ſay for Arch-biſhops, and Biſhops, Their <hi>government,</hi> their <hi>office,</hi> their <hi>Name.</hi> Come, gird up your loynes, and ſpeake like a man; What ſay you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Truly I have much to ſay, yet nothing at all againſt that you have ſpoken from the word of God, and Judgement from His mouth, upon the Biſhops. I can yeeld unto your hearts deſire, That our two Arch-biſhops ought to be thruſt-out; Nay, more, That thoſe two (I ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a third, The <hi>Primate</hi> of <hi>Ireland)</hi> ought to be hanged-up by the necks; for, wee know what one has don; and it is as legible what the other does; he fights ſtoutly for the Pope his Lord; I could yeeld you-up ſome of the Biſhops too, to the Juſtice of the Law, to be hanged by the neck, or <hi>roſted in the fire;</hi> I could yeeld you up our <hi>Wren, &amp;c.</hi> But to tell you, what grieveth mee, I cannot endure to heare all the Biſhops jumbled together, like Cheſt-men in a bagg, honeſt men and—toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Two Metropolitan Biſhops, &amp; one <hi>Primate</hi> together; <hi>Great men,</hi> and <hi>mean men,</hi> together; vile men, and precious men, together; you have made no diſtinction; I profeſſe unto you, you have ſo confounded the perſons, that I cannot finde out the <hi>Primate</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor difference him from another Biſhop, (now he is in <hi>Oxford)</hi> where all the Biſhops are, or where all their hearts are: You have made ſuch a mingle-mangle one with another, that I cannot ſingle-out Biſhop <hi>Wren,</hi> that vile man, from Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> that precious man: You have, as I ſaid at firſt, jum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them together, like Cheſt-men in a bagg: You ſhould have conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, how ſoundly ſome of them have preached, [but ſome; ſome not at all; very few oftener than once a yeare, and then not ſoundly neither] what good bookes they have written. And touching the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> how cleare they are for the innocency of the ſame. All this you ſhould have conſidered, and not have jumbled them all together. Indeed I am grieved, that you cannot diſtinguiſh better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Truly I would grieve no honeſt man; and I hope to cleare my words ſo unto you, That they ſhall be no griefe to your heart. You ſay I have jumbled the Biſhops all together, like Cheſt-men in a bagge. Ile anſwer you to that firſt, and grant, ſo I have done, and purpoſely I have done it, for mightie reaſon, for ſo they jumbled the dayes of the weeke, the ſeventh <hi>Day</hi> with the ſix dayes, they made no difference, no diſtinction at all. Deſtinction! No, They marred their Lords day more than any Day. I grant you, they have don ſome good workes; <q>So did <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> greater workes than they; But <hi>Alexander</hi> killed his deare friend <hi>Caliſthenes;</hi> Him, who dearly loved <hi>Alexander,</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154605:14"/> the King both; and ever after that, when it was alledged for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Alexander, That he had don ſuch and ſuch great things;</hi> It was checked with this; <hi>He did ſo indeed,</hi> but <hi>he killed his true and honeſt friend, Caliſthenes,</hi> he <hi>killed him;</hi>
                  </q> And that darkened all his glory to his dying day. So when it is ſaid, The Biſhops, ſome few of them, have written good bookes; Yes, but <hi>they have polluted the Lords Day;</hi> which, if there were no more, is enough, to ſtain their glory, while the world ſtands; But there is more. Have they, the beſt of them, anſwered their names? have they <hi>magnified their office?</hi> have they given <hi>attendance to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Ezek. 22. 30. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>reading, to exhortation, to doctrine?</hi> or, when The LORD <hi>ſought</hi> for a <hi>man</hi> amongſt them, I ſay a <hi>man</hi> *, to ſpeake for Him, was there a man amongſt them, the Biſhops all, that did appeare? They ſhould have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken His people by the hand now in this day of their trouble, doe they <note place="margin">A man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that has the <hi>fire</hi> of zeal in him, will ſtand in the breach till hee has <hi>hedged-up</hi> the <hi>hedge.</hi>
                  </note> doe it? I ſay againe, doe they doe it? or doe they take the people of GOD by their throats? GOD is witneſſe, even GOD is witneſſe. He is witneſſe alſo, What blaſphemies they have heard belched-out from the Pulpit, and they were ſilent the while, and afterwards. What hard words have they heard in the Court, pointed out againſt His <hi>hidd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n ones,</hi> which they reproved not? Reproved not! encouraged rather; God knowes, what ungodly deeds they have ſeene! and how the beſt of the Biſhops have ſtrengthened the hand of the wicked, doing violence to the godly! GOD knows all this; He knowes, even the <hi>Holy One,</hi> who tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the reines, and ſearcheth the hearts, &amp; underſtanddeth the thoughts long before. He knowes, That the beſt of them have dealt moſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly in His matters; moſt treacherouſly with His people in the Day of viſitation; moſt wickedly in the Covenant; <hi>The beſt of them is a briar;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mich. 7. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> moſt upright is ſharper than a thorne-hedge; The day of Thy Watchmen and Thy viſitation cometh, now ſhall be their p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rplexitie,</hi> Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot joyne with you; You ſhould have pulled out the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate</hi> hence, and Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> before you had ſaid <hi>Amen;</hi> Why man, The LORD bids you put a difference betwixt the good and the bad; the precious and the vile; And, when the LORD viſits a people in wrath <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Exo. 8. 22 <hi>B.</hi> 9. 4. 11. 17. <hi>Aug. de civit. Dei, l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. See <hi>Cure of feares.</hi> pag. 33.</note> and indignation, then He ſets a marke, He makes a ſeperation, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellouſly ſeperateth</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">a</hi>. <hi>B.</hi> He do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> indeed, then He <hi>ſets apart,</hi> then He ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates indeed. Then He ſets a marke, a legible marke, a proper and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar marke upon His choſen ones. But not viſible to a common eye; as it was in the 4. Pſalme, and other places. No; good and bad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the precious, and the vile, are carried away with the ſame floud of GODS wrath; there is no diſtinction made to your outward eye, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons intimated before, more fully ſet downe in that notable Chapter,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154605:14"/> pointed to in the margin <hi rend="sup">b</hi>; But becauſe I finde your ſpirit grieved, Ile open the ſacred Records, and reade what wee finde there; <hi>This, That</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 25. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſrael joyned himſelfe unto Baal-Peor</hi> (an abominable Idoll:) <hi>and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of The LORD was kindled againſt Iſrael.</hi> What was <hi>Iſraels</hi> Idolatry <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Primari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s populi,</hi> Iun.</note> to their Governors, and Chief-taines, the <hi>Heads</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">c</hi>? Yes to them, and they muſt ſuffer for it. What! The people joyned to <hi>Baal-Peor,</hi> and the <hi>Heads</hi> of the people lookers-on! They muſt be hanged up all for that. It is the Charge of the LORD; <hi>Take all the heads of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and hang them up. All the heads;</hi> you will obſerve that, <hi>All.</hi> Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, ſome <hi>heads</hi> did not contrive for the ſetting up, or ſerving <hi>that ſhame</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Hoſ. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> Nay, doubtleſſe ſome <hi>heads,</hi> there, thought the ſetting up <hi>that ſhame,</hi> and ſerving before it, To be as abominable, as any <hi>heads</hi> amongſt us judged the Declaration for ſports <hi>(that ſhame)</hi> to be, even ſo abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. Nay, doubtleſſe, could they have maintained their honours, and head-ſhips amongſt and over the people, they would have withſtood that abominable ſervice, the peoples joyning to <hi>Baal-Peor, that ſhame;</hi> But not one, not one <hi>man</hi> was found, that would doe as <hi>Phineas</hi> did; not a <hi>man,</hi> that would ſhow his head appearing for GOD, and againſt <hi>that ſhame:</hi> Therefore, <hi>Take all the heads, and hang them up;</hi> Where? <hi>Before The LORD,</hi> before whoſe glorious eye, they committed that abomination; And becauſe not one of theſe men would ſhew their <hi>heads,</hi> would appeare for their Lord; hang them up <hi>before the Sun;</hi> put them <hi>to ſhame;</hi> make them a publike example; ſhew them openly; make them a ſpectacle; ſet their heads before that <hi>Sun</hi> (which they made an Idoll) that all may point at them with the finger, and ſay, <hi>Theſe are they, who did ſlinke away, who hid their heads, would not appeare when time was,</hi> for <hi>their Great Lord,</hi> and <hi>Maſter in heaven:</hi> Now they doe appeare; Now they are ſhowen openly <hi>before the Sun.</hi> It muſt be ſo don, it ought to be ſo don for GOD has ſaid it; <hi>Take all the HEADS of the people, and hang them-up before the LORD againſt the Sun, that the feirce anger of the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 25. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>LORD may be turned away from Iſrael.</hi> Looke you well upon it, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it well, and you muſt conclude from hence, That all the Biſhops, the chiefe, the <hi>Primate,</hi> and <hi>Metropolitan,</hi> the great men, and mean men, all muſt be <hi>thruſt downe,</hi> all <hi>caſt-out:</hi> Ile carry it no higher than to a <hi>thruſting downe,</hi> a <hi>caſting-out; Hang them-up before the LORD, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sun,</hi> That I leave to the Judges, as it followes*; But if you <note place="margin">Verſ. 5. 6.</note> will not yeeld ſo farr for the Thruſting all the Biſhops downe, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting them all out; Then I muſt ſay, you are the man, who will not be ſatisfied from reaſon, or Scripture, nor from the mouth and command of GOD.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:154605:15"/>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſatisfied; I yeeld them up all patiently to the Juſtice of the Law: And I ſay now, <hi>Currat lex ſiat juſticia, ruat mundus;</hi> Let the Law have its courſe; let Juſtice be don, though the earth ſhake, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes be moved, yea, ſhattered to pieces, let Juſtice be done. Amen, But</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>What another <hi>But</hi> yet, and ſo out of place! you are not ſatisfied, I perceive, touching this <hi>All.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that I am, content, That all theſe Arch-biſhops (they are but two) be thruſt out; And all theſe Biſhops every man; <hi>Take them, even All the heads, and &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Speak out man, the terror of an Arch-biſhop, or a Lord, cannot make you afraid now, GOD will be terrible to them, ſpeake out; <hi>And hang them-up before the Sun</hi> that followes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>True, But I was ſpeaking for them, yet indeed I am aſhamed, but I conſider, All your Allegations are but <hi>vitia perſonarum,</hi> theſe may be thruſt away, or hanged-up before the Sun, and others thruſt into their places, for indeed Arch-biſhips are venerable for their <hi>Antiquitie.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Ah Lord! What a word is that! The ſame word will ſerve to eſtabliſh <hi>errour,</hi> very ancient, Truth, its <hi>oppoſite,</hi> but a few hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es before it. Venerable for Antiquitie! You may ſay as much for the Devill too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that old Serpent. Venerable for Antiquitie! So is <hi>Sunday</hi> and <hi>Monday,</hi> and ſo through the whole weeke, (and <hi>Saints</hi> dayes, as we fooles miſcall them) anciently called by thoſe names by the Heathen in honour to the <hi>Sun,</hi> and to the Queen of heaven. Venerable for Antiquitie! So is the Pope too, and his <hi>Cardinalls</hi> more ancient than he, if you will beleeve them, or their <hi>Advocate;</hi> for he and they conclude from ſacred Scripture too, (ſee what Interpreters they are) <hi>That the Cardinalls are two dayes older than the Moone;</hi> They were in the firmament of the Church, before the <hi>Moone</hi> was ſet in the heaven, as they collect very wiſely from the Text <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 8 See <hi>Childs patrimony pag.</hi> 104.</note> pointed to in the Margin; I will not contend with you, nor you with me; you ſhall have your ſaying, <hi>Arch-biſhops are venerable for their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitis:</hi> So you ſay, ſo I ſay; wee are agreed: Arch-biſhops are as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient as <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> as <hi>Heatheniſme</hi> in this Land: They were here before the Land was Chriſtian; And now that this Land muſt be the LORDS <hi>Land,</hi> and the people there, The LORDS <hi>people,</hi> Chriſtians <hi>indeed,</hi> now ſhall Arch biſhops be no more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Let Antiquitie goe, I ſee it will doe them no good, but a <hi>neceſſitie</hi> there is, there ſhould be Arch-biſhops.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>A neceſſitie! then there is <hi>reaſon</hi> for it, and <hi>Law</hi> both: but there is neither; He be as plaine with you as a pack-ſtaff. Tell mee. when I have told you; There ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeverall flocks of ſheepe in the Land, a Shepheard
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154605:15"/> over every flock; ſo carefull wee are of our ſheepe, that harmleſſe, uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cattell: And great reaſon for that; Now tell me; What <hi>reaſon</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> is there, That there ſhould be a great, a <hi>Catholique</hi> Shepheard to <hi>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erſee</hi> all theſe Shepheards; have you any <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> for that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>No truly, That there ſhould be a great <hi>Overſeer</hi> over ſmall <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I thought ſo; Therefore I know there is no <hi>neceſſitie.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt grant it; but there is a <hi>Decency.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>A Decency! worſe and worſe; You ſhould remember your charge, To ſpeake as the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acle of GOD, and as in the eares of GOD. You doe not anſwer your charge, when you ſay, That the being of Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops in a Church, makes for the <hi>decency</hi> in the Church. I anſwer you, there are not <hi>Arch-Angells</hi> in heaven: And is it <hi>decent,</hi> there ſhould be <hi>Arch biſhops</hi> or <hi>Primates</hi> on earth? There is no <hi>decency</hi> in it at all. I know you will forſake that Argument.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Well: But they ſay, there can not be a <hi>glorious</hi> Church without Arch-biſhops.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>A foppery! I had almoſt ſaid a blaſphemy; I ſhall ſay it anon. The Church is <hi>glorious</hi> in heaven, you will ſay, and yet there be no <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> there, all men ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I have heard them highly extolled, commended, and praiſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>For what, for their vertues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>So was <hi>Hildebrand</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Beno Cardinalis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventinus,</hi> making his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to ſpeak of Pope <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debrand,</hi> ſaith thus; Now muſt I ſpeake of warres, ſlaughters, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, killing of fathers ſtrives, hatreds, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, robberies, ſpolings, of common treaſure, ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of Churches, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and ſeditions more then civill.</note> the Pope praiſed, who had poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned ſix Popes his predec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſours, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a Conjurer and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of Devils and threw the Sacrament into the fire. This man <hi>was commended for his vertues. Judas</hi> has been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended above the Apoſtles. Commended! Is that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny newes, when Robbers, Murtherers, Rebels, Traitors, vile, and treacherous Prieſts, and perſons are highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended at this day; they are honoured, dignified, titles of grace and honour are conferred upon them? To ſay all in a word, the Anti-Parliament, the Parliament in Oxford, conſiſting of the out-caſts from this Parliament, Oxford Parliament I ſay, the refuſe, the <hi>garbage</hi> of the land, that Parliament is commended. Will you put any force in praiſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations? I pray you know from me, that a <hi>quartane Ague</hi> has been praiſed: ſo has <hi>folly</hi> been exalted by very learned men. Nay, I could read you a long oration in the praiſe of a <hi>Louſe.</hi> If I ſhould tell you what perſons and flatuous things have been commended, I ſhould make
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154605:16"/> you laugh heartily. But we are ſerious. Certainly that Argument will not hold neither. But to ſpeak-out plainly, and all in a word. It is blaſphemy for a man to take unto himſelfe that honour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I grant it to be blaſphemy in the <hi>Popes</hi> mouth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>In the Popes mouth! It is blaſphemy in the mans mouth, who will aſſume unto himſelfe that name (that incommunicable name) <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> or <hi>Primat,</hi> for he is Pope, the mouth that ſpeaks blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as truly Pope in London, as <hi>Pope Leo</hi> was in Rome. To diſpatch this, and to cleare your judgement from the cleareſt light; I pray you conſider, That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Bleſſed for ever, is (if I might uſe our Dialect) the Archbiſhop and Primat in <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>earth:</hi> And the <hi>Seaven Spirits</hi> is His <hi>Vicar-generall;</hi> He is the great Shepheard, the ſole Monarch, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords.</hi> And becauſe the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the world, and Lords of the earth; becauſe Almighty Kings (in their conceit, thinking they have an arme like God, and ſo) Lord-like Biſhops, have ſet themſelves againſt this <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>King;</hi> therefore has this <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>King</hi> ſet his face againſt them: He has taken to Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>power,</hi> and an Iron rod into his hand, and now we ſee him <hi>thraſh the Nations like ſtraw, and the Hills like chaffe:</hi> and <hi>comming upon Princes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 41. 15. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>as</hi> upon <hi>mortor:</hi> Now we ſee him ſmiting the earth <hi>terribly,</hi> nor will he leave ſmiting till the bloodſhed there bee diſcovered; till the gods there be ſtarved, till the Idols there be caſt out to the <hi>Moles</hi> and to the <hi>Batts;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 2.</note> now we ſee him ſhaking Kingdomes and Crownes, nor will he leave ſhaking, till he have ſhat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered and broken them to peeces, becauſe they would not be the Lords Kingdomes, nor would they with the <hi>Elders, caſt down their crownes before the Throne.</hi> If they continue obſtinate, if <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 4: 10</note> they will not rule for Chriſt, if they will not ſubmit unto Him, then thus and thus the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> will do unto them, that all the Kingdomes of the earth may know, The <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> reigneth, there is a <hi>God,</hi> that <hi>judgeth in the earth.</hi> But who ſhall bold out while hee ſees theſe things accompliſhed? They that wait patiently for the Lord, (for here is the patience of the Saints) They that leave God to his own <hi>time, worke</hi> and <hi>way;</hi> doe their own work faithfully, take hold of the Almighty arme, wrap up their ſoules in a promiſe touching this matter, ſo they are at peace: And this peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall keep their hearts in <hi>perfect peace,</hi> peace, peace, Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you have not done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> indeed have I, unleſſe you have any more to ſay for Arch-biſhops; have you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Not a word; I could bite my tongue for ſaying ſo much. But I have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154605:16"/> much to ſay for Biſhops, that others may be put into their rooms, that the Biſhops government may be continued, their office, and their <hi>name.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee you will trouble me, and I am content with the trouble, ſo it may eaſe your mind, and give you content. But touching the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Biſhops, I thought verily you were reſolved clearly, and fully, that it is Antichriſtian, are you not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>No indeed not I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee your memory fails you, not your underſtanding; you have underſtood that the <hi>head</hi> of this bulky body is <hi>reprobate ſilver;</hi> what will you think then of the other members of this body? What of the taile? What of the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot? Nay, you underſtand that the <hi>head</hi> of this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy (nay the <hi>heads,</hi> and that argues it is a monſtrous body) the Arch-biſhop, is ſtruck-off by his own hand, <hi>a ſlain man</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">An Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later is a <hi>ſlain man: I will caſt down your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lain men.</hi> Ezek. 6. 4.</note>. For to ſay all in a word, which you heard before; in that <hi>head</hi> is the mouth that ſpeakes blaſphemies, he is a <hi>ſlain man,</hi> caſt out as an abominable branch. Will you plead now for any part of this body: For the <hi>ſhoulders?</hi> they are the Biſhops. Or the <hi>Belly?</hi> That is their Courts. Or the <hi>Thighes?</hi> They are the Chancellours, Commiſſaries. Or <hi>Feet?</hi> They are their Proctors, and Doctors, what ſhall I call them? They are the Biſhops <hi>Purvayers,</hi> and <hi>Caterers,</hi> to ſerve the Biſhops luſts and their own: Will you contend for theſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I tell you, I contend for the government by Biſhops.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>A government! If you have the government, you muſt have the governours, Archbiſhops and Biſhops, Archdeacons and Deacons, Chancellours and Commiſſaries, you muſt have their Courts too, with their Doctors and Proctors there, the moſt notorious—, I want a word whereby to expreſſe their villanies and notorious inſolencies; you muſt have that—garbage too, their Emiſſaries, their <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> thoſe execrable rabble that ſtink all the world over. All theſe you muſt have. Will you contend for theſe? or will you have all this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious government and governours ſink down and fall into the earth, from which it had its riſe and originall, after the Archbiſhops?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I would have the government ſtand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You would anger a Saint! pray you conſider, the Biſhops are but the Archbiſhops hands: the other officers (not worth the record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) are but <hi>Instruments</hi> in the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhops hands. Will you contend that theſe brethren in iniquity, inſtruments of the Divell, that theſe ſhould be reſerved and <hi>kept alive;</hi> will you contend for this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yes indeed will I, life is a pretious thing: Ile pray that they may
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154605:17"/> be <hi>kept alive,</hi> that is, that the Governours may continue in their <hi>full force, power and vertue,</hi> notwithſtanding any law (though Gods law) to the contrary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>A pittifull man! But it is a fooliſh pitty, and ſpoils a Citie and Kingdome both: had you lived in the dayes of <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> you would have been a very earneſt ſutor to him, That <hi>Achans ſilver, his garment, and his wedge of gold, and his ſonnes and his daughters, and his oxen and his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioſ. 7. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>aſſes, and his ſheep and his tent, and all that he had, might be preſerved, would you not?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſurely, it would have grieved me to have ſeen all thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and things to periſh before mine eye, as it grieved the <hi>Singing-men</hi> that were in <hi>Pauls,</hi> to ſee the Prieſts—(what doe you call them) ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiments, or horſe trappings, to be burnt there before their noſes: ſo it would have grieved me to have ſeen ſuch an execution, ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You have more wit then you ſhew: for in ſhewing your pitty, you had ſeemed wiſer then <hi>Joſua</hi> and all Iſrael; For <hi>Joſhua and all Iſrael with him took Achan, and all the forementioned with him,</hi> ſtoned him and them: then burnt <hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>things.</hi> (Doe you mark that? <hi>ſton'd</hi> them firſt, and <hi>burnt</hi> them after; ſtoning was not enough, they muſt be burnt too) Then they raiſed a monument there, and there they ſet a marke, they called it <hi>the valley of Achor:</hi> (i. e.) a <hi>valley of trouble,</hi> and perple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xitie: <hi>Achan</hi> had <hi>troubled</hi> all Iſrael, he and all his muſt be troubled for that, neither <hi>perſons</hi> nor <hi>things</hi> muſt be ſpared. <hi>Junius</hi> gives us a large note upon the place, the ſum is, to teach us, <hi>how contagious a thing ſin is, and how execrable the inſtruments of ſin are.</hi> Can you apply this to the perſons and things in hand?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yes I thank God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>That is well; but if you can apply it indeed, you will be aware you doe not your ſelfe <hi>trouble</hi> Iſrael: nor will you have a word to ſay for them that are <hi>troublers</hi> there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Not a word for <hi>Troublers,</hi> yet I muſt ſpeak for the government: for indeed we idolize it, we dote upon it, we muſt have it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>If there were no other reaſon but that, for the abolition of that government, that were enough; <hi>wee make it an Idol, wee dote upon it,</hi> therefore it ſhall be taken away. But will we have the <hi>Government</hi> ſtill, then we muſt have the <hi>Governours</hi> ſtill. And now if I ſhould tell you what horrible, prodigious, execrable,—(I want a word) mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, villanies, have been committed by thoſe <hi>Governors</hi> and their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, (ſlaves rather) I ſhould make your eares tingle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:154605:17"/>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I think ſo too: But you could tell me no more then the faults of perſons only, and their Courts, no more. Might not the <hi>perſons</hi> bee purged, and the <hi>Courts</hi> too, and the <hi>government</hi> preſerved? Though there be no Catholique Biſhop (an Archbiſhop) yet might there be a <hi>Dioceſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Biſhop. And now I have told you what we would have, (and our meaning) a <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Biſhop we would have.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Very well: But you muſt explain your meaning now, what doe you mean by a <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Biſhop? Or what is a Dioceſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tell: It is Greek to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>To me alſo <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>. But you a ſtrange man to conclude for that, which is Greek to you, you underſtand not: You contend for a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop over his <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> and you know not what his <hi>Dioceſſe</hi> is. Ile tell you as well as I can, for it is a ſtrange word. <q>A <hi>Dioceſſe</hi> is a government in an houſe, or in the place we commonly call the Church, and they have ſtretched it all over the Citie and Countrey;</q> I mean, they have enlarged the <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> they have ſo out compaſſed it, that all the Biſhops in the land, were they Biſhops <hi>indeed,</hi> could not be ſufficient for that place, to fill up ſuch a roomth: they have rendred it ſo capacious, that their <hi>Dioceſſe</hi> containes more roomth, then <hi>Philippi,</hi> a Citie in <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> contained, and yet they allow but one Biſhop there, whereas by the expreſſe word of GOD, there ought to be <hi>Biſhops and Deacons</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Philip. 1. 1.</note>. To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you yet more fully, I will tell you a ſtory. A requeſt was made, (who made it, or to whom, is not pertinent) for ſuch a length of ground as an Oxes-hide would cover (or rather be ſtretched unto.) A modeſt requeſt, it was granted; a ſmall ſpot of ground would be cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with an Oxes skin. The petitioners make much of the gift; for they did not doe as our Curriers doe, and as <hi>Homer,</hi> after his manner, relates the manner very fully, they did not tugg at it to ſtretch it out, that it might fill-up as much as poſſibly the <hi>hide</hi> could hold: But they cut large <hi>thongs</hi> out of it, as we ſay, and ſo ſtretched and tentered thoſe <hi>thongs,</hi> that they could reach over ſo much ground, as thereon to build a Citie as capacious as <hi>Philippi</hi> was, King <hi>Philips</hi> towne, and there they placed, if I well remember, one Regent. Here was a notable policie to get ground. Truly the Biſhop has dealt as politickly with the <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> he has made it wide, and large, he has cut large <hi>thongs</hi> out of it, he has gained much ground (if all be gain that comes to <hi>his</hi> hand) he has built a palace thereon, and found a Lordſhip there; and there he (was) there he had elbow-roomth enough, and was a <hi>Lord</hi> in his Dioceſſe. Do you underſtand what an over-grown thing this <hi>Dioceſſe</hi> is? How the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop hath lengthened it? what incomes the Biſhop hath from it?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154605:18"/> what proviſions were made for him there? And yet <hi>Lucullus coenat cum Lucullo</hi> [as he ſaid when he had prepared a ſupper for a King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which he al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne did partake of.] All theſe proviſions and preparations are but for one Biſhop: all this to cram and fatten one <hi>Capon</hi> (that was his name who was predeceſſor to Mr. <hi>Juel</hi> (of him anon) as <hi>vile</hi> as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was <hi>pretious.</hi> You know a <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Biſhop now, and what his Dioceſſe is; A monſtrous thing, wherein I know not how many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pariſhes are crowded-up together, that there may bee more roomth for the Lord. You underſtand this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I thank you; I underſtand your meaning fully, <hi>That you would have a Biſhop in every Pariſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>My underſtanding is not cleare there: For to be briefe with you; Firſt, I doe not allow of the <hi>name</hi> Biſhop; and I beleeve, when I ſhall have told you ſomthing about it, as I ſhall anon, you will not allow the <hi>name</hi> neither. 2. And for a <hi>Pariſh,</hi> I doe not well underſtand that diviſion, or who made that diſtinction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Can you tell what you would have?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I thank God; I would have in ſuch a place as <hi>Philippi</hi> was, <hi>Biſhops and Deacons,</hi> for that is according to Gods expreſſe will. <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 1.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Very true: But how many Biſhops and Deacons muſt there be for ſuch a place as <hi>Philippi</hi> was?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tell the number. But there muſt bee a Biſhop and Deacons for every Dioceſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>So think I too: one Biſhop for one Dioceſſe, <hi>non eſt elenchus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nos,</hi> we are agreed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>True; but then it muſt not be a <hi>Dioceſſe</hi> ſtretched out and tente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as the Oxes-hide was, beyond all imagination. We were conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded even now, that that is properly a <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> which one man can o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſee: and whereunto his voyce can reach, when his people are aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in their <hi>meeting-place.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>A meeting-place! Why not a Church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Your queſtion is not to purpoſe, therefore you ſhall have no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Can you except againſt any word, that has been laſt ſpoken tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> and the Biſhop there? that is the queſtion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>In effect I have anſwered already, No, for what you have ſpoken, is the expreſſe <hi>will</hi> and <hi>word</hi> of GOD. But you ſeem to hold, that there is no <hi>ſuperiority</hi> in the Church: quit your ſelfe there firſt, that I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve others touching that great objection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>That I will: Theſe words <hi>Biſhops and Deacons</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Tit. 1. 5.</note>, (not my words) hold forth the contrary, ſo alſo theſe, <hi>and ordain Elders</hi> 
                  <hi rend="sup">a</hi>: Theſe words
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154605:18"/> doe inferre, not onely, That the Miniſters are above their people; but that there is a <hi>ſuperioritie</hi> amongſt themſelves; nature, ſenſe, reaſon; the naturall body, if wee ſhould goe over it, and obſerve the parts from top to toe, will cleare all this. There is the <hi>head,</hi> and ſo downward; put your finger into your mouth (that is the little worlds <hi>heaven)</hi> there are <hi>upper</hi> and <hi>lower</hi> teeth, but all doe the ſame ſervice for the body. It is ſo in the <hi>body politique;</hi> There are ſome for <hi>Counſell,</hi> they are <hi>heads;</hi> Some for <hi>direction,</hi> they are <hi>eyes;</hi> Some to <hi>uphold</hi> and beare up others, they are <hi>ſhoulders;</hi> Some for <hi>action,</hi> they are <hi>hands;</hi> It is ſo in the houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, two houſes they ſay; there are <hi>Speakers</hi> in both, to whom all turne themſelves when they ſpeake; Superiours for the time, and when the worke is done, then there may be a change. It is ſo in every Court, a Chaire there, and ſome one ſitting in it. It is ſo in the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines;</hi> every where, in Church, Chappell, Houſe. It is fit it ſhould be ſo, nay, it muſt be ſo. What a fond conceit is it then to thinke, That there cannot be <hi>Over-ſeers</hi> in the Church, but they muſt be <hi>everlasting Lords,</hi> and as perpetuall <hi>Dictators?</hi> There is a deſtinction of gifts, of graces; therefore of perſons, and of places. How groſſe a miſtake now to thinke, That wee allow of no <hi>Superiours,</hi> becauſe wee abhorre thoſe that have <hi>Lorded</hi> it over the LORDS inheritance? Wee doe indeed, for it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe againſt the command of GOD. I might be large here; but you are a ſober man; you are ſatisfied touching <hi>Superiours;</hi> and I have quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelfe at that point, have I not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed you have. But now, That wee are, as our vowes are upon us, throwing-down and rooting-out the Hierarchy, that Antichriſtian, that curſed Government; Its friends make clamours againſt us; Ile tell you what they ſay very briefly, (for ſo you will anſwer I am ſure,) They bring Scripture, and object firſt; <hi>That wee ſpeake evill of Dignities.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jude 8. Verſe 10.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Bid them ſay on, <hi>things, which wee know not;</hi> Then bid them prove, That wee know not, what the Dignities of Arch-biſhops and Biſhops have been: or know not, that they <hi>be evill:</hi> Bid them prove that; but that they can never doe; wee know thoſe Dignities are <hi>evill;</hi> and ſith they call <hi>evill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> good,</hi> woe unto them. What ſay they next? They ſpeak Scripture ſtill; So did the Devill too; What is it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>That the Arch-biſhops and Biſhops, are <hi>Powers:</hi> Therefore not to be reſiſted, for there muſt be <hi>no reſiſting of Powers.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Bid them reade on; <hi>That are ordained of God.</hi> Now bid them prove, that Arch-biſhops and Lord Biſhops, &amp;c. <hi>are ordained of GOD;</hi> are the <hi>ordinance of God.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I have enough to choak my adverſaries now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:154605:19"/>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>No, but you have not, They will goe on with the argument, but marke how they proceed; Juſt as a boy that goes upon his head, his heeles are upward, and ſo he ſpurnes againſt heaven; Juſt ſo, theſe kinde of men will goe-on, till they have wrought out this concluſion; <hi>That the Devill and mans will are to be obeyed;</hi> Their Reaſon, <hi>for they are</hi> POVVERS; <hi>and all powers are of God;</hi> doe you obſerve?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, very well, and I am ſure, I ſhall be too hard for my Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> takes away the honour (Lord) from the Biſhop, &amp; leaves him the <hi>work:</hi> The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop does clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, takes to himſelf all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and leaves the work. <hi>Lib.</hi> 19. <hi>ca.</hi> 19. 1 Tim 3. 1 Theſ. 2. 7, 8, 9.</note> at that argument. But I have two words, wherein I would be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied before wee come to a full ſtop; The one is touching the <hi>office</hi> of a Biſhop; the other is, touching the <hi>name.</hi> Concerning both, great things and honourable are ſpoken, even by GOD Himſelfe. Touching the <hi>office</hi> firſt; Can you except againſt it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>No indeed can I not; I cannot except againſt a <hi>good worke,</hi> and that <hi>is the office;</hi> To give the minde to reading, to exhortation, and to do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>that is the office.</hi> Naturally to care for the children, exhorting, comforting, charging them (as <hi>a Father doth</hi> thence his dutie is conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) <hi>That is the office.</hi> To be gentle among the Children, knowing them by name; <hi>affectionately</hi> deſirous after them, provoaking them by teares; and as a nurſe, cheriſhing them; <hi>That is the office.</hi> It cannot be blamed, nor the Biſhop neither. I mean the man, for he is a <hi>father, a nurſe;</hi> he is that which ſtands in the neareſt relation, importing the tendreſt care, and deareſt affection, and he is blameleſſe in all. How dare you or I blame him, whom GOD commends?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>So ſay my Adverſaries too; The office is not to be blamed, nor the Biſhop; You ſee both are as ancient as <hi>Paul</hi> was; And you know too, That a Reverend Father of the Church, has calculated the nativitie of the Biſhops, and the deſcent of the <hi>office,</hi> and he finds the <hi>office</hi> in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and the Biſhops before the ancient Kings in this Land.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Very true all this. And now you need not tell your Adverſaries, That the Reverend Father is anſwered by the Sonnes of the Church; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or that he ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed heaven in the face ſo long, that, at laſt, he fell into the Ditch: You need not tell your Adverſaries this, for they know it well enough. I could tell you now a notable Story, as judicious <hi>Calvin</hi> tells it mee, concerning <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperour, a notable Story, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pertinent; but I will not trouble you with it, onely point at it in the Margin <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Calvin</hi> upon <hi>Iſa. cap.</hi> 19. 11.</note>; And ſo queſtion you a little; Doe you thinke, that <hi>Paul</hi> means by <hi>office,</hi> and <hi>Biſhop,</hi> the Government of a Catholique and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Biſhop, (an Arch-biſhop) or Dioceſan, and Lord Biſhop, doe you thinke ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tell what to thinke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:154605:19"/>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>No; why I told you before, their office cannot be found in the earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>They have found it in heaven.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>So preſumptuouſly they ſaid, and now you ſee, though they will, not, that they are brought downe <hi>to the ſides of the pitt;</hi> You ſhould not put mee to repetition, for indeed, what I ſpake of their Government, might have ſufficed for their <hi>office.</hi> But reade the Text againe. The <hi>office</hi> is a <hi>good worke,</hi> cannot you tell your Adverſaries now, what <hi>worke</hi> they have made in the Church, and Common-wealth? I know you can. You reade alſo, That the office of <hi>Pauls</hi> Biſhop was <hi>naturally</hi> to care for his people; as a father, as a nurſe. His office was to feed the flock of Chriſt. The mightie word of GOD, was the <hi>Scepter</hi> of <hi>Pauls</hi> Biſhop, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he caſt downe <hi>ſtrong holds: ſtrong rodds</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Ezek. 19. 11.</note> were <hi>the Scepter</hi> of theſe B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhops; Theſe did not <hi>feed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> but <hi>rule</hi> the ſheepe of Chriſt with a <hi>rod of Iron</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 2. 27. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſignifies, <hi>He ſhall feed, or rule.</hi> The Pope and his Biſh. make the later to be the <hi>office</hi> of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; So the ſheepe have had a hard fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from that inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</note>. You reade againe; <hi>Pauls</hi> Biſhop <hi>muſt be blameleſſe:</hi> were theſe ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>What is all this to the <hi>office?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I told you before, and I will repeat it but this once, Their <hi>office</hi> is not found in heaven, or earth. It is true; If wee beleeve them, they have found their office in heaven, and have executed it upon earth (as wee heard) but who will obſerve the whole Series of things, ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne plainly, That <hi>a curſe has cleaven to their office evermore, cloſer than the Ivy to the wall; or the morter betwxt the joyning of the ſtones:</hi> As it alwayes does to that office, which is not of Gods ordaining, and for which, no man (though for his ſinceritie, honeſtie, learning, without exception) can be ſufficient. I will not recall here what was ſaid, how croſſe <hi>Catholick</hi> Biſhops, Lord, or Dioceſan Biſhops, are to God, and His Word. I will onely ſay what ſome have ſaid of the Pope, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to ours; <q>Some Popes have been Fathers, but never any Pope an holy Father; And ſome few, very few, good men, But never any, a good Pope. So alſo as true of our Biſhops, looke wee over them all, wee may finde ſome <hi>good men</hi> (very few) but not one Good Biſhop.</q> And this, I muſt ever thinke, is by vertue of the curſe, which cleaveth to the <hi>office.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I am in a worſe caſe to anſwer my Adverſary now, than before. <hi>Never any a good Biſhop!</hi> Many good Biſhops, ſay my Adverſaries, for many of them were martyrs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Not many, if I remember, <hi>five onely;</hi> but twice five were <hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> Five martyrs will not argue ſo ſtrongly for the goodneſſe of the <hi>office,</hi> as twice five againſt it. Againe, Martyrdome does not make a good Biſhop; he muſt render himſelfe good while he lives, by <hi>magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his office.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:154605:20"/>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Well, and ſo they did. Biſhop <hi>Ridley,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Latimer;</hi> What can you ſay againſt them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Nothing, not a word, God has accepted them, He has pardoned, It <hi>ſhall be remembred no more;</hi> how Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> dealt with King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Saint; he would, but I forbeare. Nor how Biſhop <hi>Latimer,</hi> that good man, over-taken through Infirmitie, did, in a Sermon, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with a murtherer, againſt the good Kings Uncle, the good Lord Protector, too like a Biſhop.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Hooper,</hi> what ſay you againſt him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Againſt him! I have much to ſay for him, an excellent man he! he had his Table full (with good cheare, you will ſay, and ſo have our Biſhops too, no) full ſet with company, (he <hi>eat not his morſels alone)</hi> and they the pooreſt of his flock, and, which I would have noted, God would have it followed, he fed their ſoules firſt from his owne mouth, and then their bodies with his meat; his doctrine did drop upon them <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 2.</note> as the raine, and his ſpeech diſtill'd as the dew. The meaning is, he Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed them firſt, and then ſaid, <hi>Eat friends, and be merry,</hi> GOD <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the worke.</hi> An excellent man. So was Biſhop <hi>Juel</hi> too, the Jewel <note place="margin">Lege vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elli.</note> of our Church, ſet as a Diamond there; <q>He gave himſelfe up to the LORD, and His worke; he ſpent and waſted a wearied body there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and gloried in it, as well he might, that ſo he did. And it greatly refreſhed his dying ſpirits, when his ſoule ſate on his lips; That he had waſted his body, and ſpirits too in the worke of the LORD, &amp;c. to whom he hath given-up his account with Joy.</q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Very well; excellent men theſe! and were not theſe good Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Look how you force me; yet I will not reply bluntly, <hi>No:</hi> But this I ſay, <q>All this argues the goodneſſe of the men; but does not argue the goodneſſe of the <hi>Office.</hi>
                  </q> They were good men; yes, and good Biſhops too: but not ſo farre as their <hi>Dioceſſe</hi> reached, for that was all over whole Shires: But ſo far as they could <hi>overſee</hi> their flocks, ſo far as they could quit themſelves as good Biſhops, catechiſing their poore people, exhorting, comforting, or as we heard, ſo farre, and not further. They were good <hi>Stewards,</hi> and faithfull in their adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (that is as much as is required) ſo farre as was poſſible for their <hi>overſight</hi> and care to reach. We think, and with reaſon, that a man cannot be ſaid to be a faithfull Steward in that houſe where hee never was, nor can know what roomes or what perſons are within. I ſay then, for I would be as plain as I can, ſo farre as their overfight could extend, (that is, to the compaſſe and extent of that <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> explained
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154605:20"/> before) ſo far they did well, no men ever before them better. Wee ſay further, and we think it is no more but what all muſt grant, That there is a point (eaſily decernible) where the creatures impotency and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe muſt neceſſarily ſet bounds to his <hi>overſight:</hi> if yet he will willingly <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtus, Candidus, Philopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c.</hi> good names, and <hi>Sapientiae,</hi> Iuſtinians Townes name, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded all, but no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour theſe names to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. <hi>Salv. lib.</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 4. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two leaves of the end. <hi>lege Naz. Orat.</hi> 21.</note> and knowingly, for ends beſt known to himſelfe, if hee will lanch-out further beyond theſe bounds, and ſo out-bound himſelfe. At that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry point of his tranſgreſſion he ſhall meet with a curſe. In ſhort, the meaning is, To that very point and part of the office, which out-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth the officer, thereto the curſe cleaveth, which the perſon may quit himſelf of, but he ſhall never quit the <hi>Office.</hi> And ſo I have done my beſt to cleare your underſtanding touching the office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed you have cleared the <hi>office</hi> of a Biſhop, now I hope you will allow us the <hi>name.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>No matter for my allowance, you need not ſtand upon that; but yet, I wiſh you would not contend for a <hi>name,</hi> an empty thing. A <hi>name!</hi> what is that, if the man be nought? <hi>Cain,</hi> a good name, the man not ſo. <hi>Abel</hi> a vain name, the man was excellent. I aſſure you, the vileſt men have had the beſt names; Popes have been called <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> both. It is true as the heathen Emperour ſaid, <hi>Nomina magna oneroſa,</hi> great names are great burthens; good names are a good engagement to fill-up, to anſwer their names. A Chriſtian King, a Chriſtian man, is an honourable name; but diſhonours him or them very much, who are not anſwerable to that name, but are againſt Chriſt all they can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray you, tell me, what is your reaſon why we ſhould relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the <hi>name?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I will; but you muſt tell me firſt, the reaſon why we ſhould retaine the name?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>That I can doe, I can give one reaſon which ſhall have more weight in it, then two of yours, it is a Scripture name, Biſhop <hi>Timothy,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Titus,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Peter,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> as I heare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You doe not well to tell me what you heare, and neglect what you read, which is this, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes of himſelfe, <hi>Who am alſo an Elder.</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 2 Iohn.</note>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>He was the chiefeſt of the Apoſtles, the Papiſts ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>There is no heed to bee taken to what they will ſay, they <hi>prattle</hi> clean contrary to what <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes of himſelfe, and <hi>Peter</hi> of himſelfe. But if you would obſerve their <hi>Acts,</hi> and one Chapter there, you would ſee it as cleare as noon day, that <hi>Peter</hi> was not the chiefe, (nay, there was no chief amongſt them) nor was he Biſhop.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:154605:21"/>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſure we have Biſhop <hi>Timothy,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Titus:</hi> for I can point to the place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You can; but neither to the chapter nor the verſe, which you might have done, if it had been <hi>Canonicall.</hi> The Biſhop hath thruſt it into our Bibles, as they have thruſt in a whole <hi>family of the Ieſuits</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 26. 44. A text as boldly perverted, and ſo has been ever ſince 1610. As are the contents before <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.</note> into our Engliſh Bibles; a notable prank. God has found them out for this, they ſhall be thruſt out, and then our Bibles ſhall be purged.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt himſelfe is called a Biſhop.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>He is not: He is called an <hi>Overſeer,</hi> and ſo he is; and by his Vicar generall, hee looks to his flock, he cares for them, he holds them faſt, not one of them ſhall be loſt or taken out of his hand. To put you out of doubt, <hi>Biſhop</hi> is not a Scripture name: for it is neither Hebrew, nor Greek, nor Latine, nor does it concerne you what it is, onely pertinent to this place it is; That it is not a Scripture name, and ſo your ſtrong reaſon, as mighty as two, proves nothing, why the name ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Now if it pleaſe you, Ile give you my reaſons why the <hi>name</hi> ſhould be aboliſhed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>It pleaſeth me very well: I pray you let me heare them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe it is a name ſo greatened and hightened, that we have not roomth enough in the world, not a place big enough, or high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to containe his Lordſhip; he has out-compaſſed a naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Let his name goe. Secondly, the <hi>name</hi> is abuſed, clean perverted, as the name <hi>Tyrant</hi> is, a good name once, and good Engliſh ſtill: for it ſignifies a King; but when the King ſtretched his power the contrary way, to the hurt of his people, in ſtead of doing them good; and to the ſubverſion of his Kingdome, and throwing downe lawes and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in ſtead of building all up; Then the name grew odious, and was aboliſhed. The ſame reaſon for the aboliſhing this name; The Biſhops, not <hi>Prelates,</hi> but <hi>Pilats;</hi> not <hi>Paſtors,</hi> but <hi>Impoſtors;</hi> not <hi>Doctors,</hi> but <hi>ſeducers,</hi> as their unreaſonable carriage has cauſed the Rime. They have made the name odious, and themſelves abominable. A ſufficient reaſon why the name ſhould be aboliſhed, and themſelves, as aforeſaid. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Biſhop</hi> is as terrible a name to ſome, as a Divell is: as pleaſing as a God to others. That neither ſide may be hurt, take it away: It is the Idoll of the land, Idolized as much in our dayes, as the <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> was in King <hi>Hez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kiahs</hi> dayes. I cannot ſubmit here to anothers judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I muſt judge it very reaſonable, That, as when the people began to put a religious honour upon the <hi>Serpent,</hi> then the King would have it called <hi>plain Braſſe.</hi> So now, ſith <hi>Biſhop</hi> is ſo idolized by the common <note place="margin">2 King. 18. 4.</note> people, let the name goe, and let the man be called a <hi>Miniſter of Ieſus</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:154605:21"/> 
                  <hi>Chriſt.</hi> If he be ſo indeed, he will like well of the <hi>name,</hi> for it is all one, as if he were called, <hi>The meſſenger of the Churches,</hi> and <hi>the glory of Chriſt.</hi> I might adde a fourth reaſon here, <hi>There is no need of the name;</hi> Caſt it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and there will be no lacke.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, ſhould I reade you a leafe in the <hi>Rhem: Teſtament,</hi> how effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the holding-up and keeping-in of <hi>names</hi> has been, for the keeping-in of abominable <hi>perſons,</hi> and <hi>things;</hi> you would yeeld mee ſo farre at leaſt, That this <hi>name Biſhop,</hi> is to be aboliſhed. I have don.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>And I am ſatisfied, and at a ſweet agreement in my ſoule, That Arch-biſhops, Lord-Biſhops, their Government and office, is to be thruſt-out; and the <hi>name</hi> aboliſhed. I pray you heartily, give me leave <hi>to weepe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You need not aske leave, you have a command for that; <hi>Weepe with them that weepe.</hi> It is ſufficient you have a <hi>command</hi> to weepe for your owne ſinnes, and others, and for the <hi>ſlaine of the people.</hi> You have example for it too; To make your couch ſwim with teares; your eyes flow like rivers; and to make the place you ſtand in a <hi>Bochim</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Judg. 1. 5</note>, a place of weeping, for reaſons many, from within, and from without; weepe and ſpare not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>To tell you the truth, I never thought of this kinde of weeping; I asked you leave to weepe for company with the <hi>Kings and Merchants of the earth;</hi> Becauſe their gods are taken away, and what have they more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>O monſtrous! weepe for company with the Kings and Merchants of the earth! This indeed is to weepe with them, that weepe; but it is to doe as thoſe women did, <hi>who ſate weeping for Tammuz.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 8. 14</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>That is Hebrew, is it not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>No nor Greeke neither; It was an <hi>Aegyptian-god,</hi> a moſt abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idoll: As comely a poſture now, for Kings and Merchants of the earth, to ſit <hi>weeping</hi> over the Hierarchy, amore abominable Idoll than was that <hi>Tammuz.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I yeeld to you heartily. But truly I intended to weepe in a merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment onely, as I have heard one did; and ſo Ile tell you a Story, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh you and my ſelfe a little; A little man, but a great Tyrant, was ferrying-over to a place, from whence he muſt never returne: And a poore Cobler, who was mightily oppreſſed by that Tyrant, was in the ſame Boat with him; The Tyrant wept heartily, for he was taken from all his gods, he ſhould ſee them no more, neither his <hi>Palaces,</hi> nor his <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> and ſo he cryed lamentably. The Ferriman, a merry fellow, would make the Cobler cry too, and ſo he did; O mee poore Cobler!
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154605:22"/> I have taken Sanctuary now at the place, <hi>where the wicked ceaſe from troubling; where the weary lie at reſt; They heare not the voyce of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</hi> O mee poore wretch! I ſhall mend ſhooes no more; I ſhall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour no more; I ſhall feele neither hunger nor thirſt any more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Ile heare no more, not a word more, though I know it might be well applyed. You have made it pretty Chriſtian, yet it is not for this place. I would have you rejoyce in all the peoples ſight, and ſing aloud for joy of heart, for ſo the upright doe. Certainly, there is the ſame cauſe now to rejoyce, as the Church had, when <hi>they went through the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 66. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>flood on foote: There did wee rejoyce in Him,</hi> (our Fathers went over, wee rejoyce:) And for the ſame reaſon, for wee ſay now, as they did then, <hi>Thy right hand, O Lord, is become glorious in power,</hi> and ſo forth; for wonderfull workes follow, as are the workes of GOD now adayes. Certainly, the Church has the ſame cauſe of rejoycing, as it had, when the <hi>great Dragon was caſt-out; Then was heard a loud voyce,</hi> ſaying, <hi>in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 12. 9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>heaven</hi> (in the Church) <hi>now is come ſalvation,</hi> &amp;c. reade it out. Certainly, the Churches time is coming, nay, it is come, when <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt be throwne downe. Therefore wee muſt now heare, <hi>a great voyce of much</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 18. 21</note> 
                  <hi>people in heaven</hi> (the Church) <hi>ſaying, Hallelujah, Salvation, and glory, and honour, and power, unto the Lord our God,</hi> Amen. <note place="margin">Rev. 19. 1.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you Sir, you have made good uſe of my fained teares, and fained mirth; you have taught mee how to doe both in good earneſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>It is an hard leſſon, heare me forth, I pray you, and The LORD grant I may heare my ſelfe. (1) If you doe weep indeed; if you are grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved indeed; then your griefe is more, That you have grieved GOD, than becauſe His and your Adverſaries have grieved you, that is firſt. (2) If you rejoyce indeed, then you rejoyce with trembling. (3.) If you prayſe GOD indeed for the workes He has done, (I cannot expreſſe how wonderfull they are) then you live to His praiſe; That is <hi>Selah;</hi> then you riſe-high in praiſes, when your life praiſeth Him, that is, when your converſation is in heaven. If God, your God, is your <hi>ſtrength;</hi> then He is your <hi>Song:</hi> If He be your <hi>Salvation,</hi> He is your <hi>praiſe</hi> too. (4.) If you long to ſee God appeare in His Glory; To ſee Him worſhipped according to His Command, in a <hi>Church-way:</hi> Then you are fitting and making your heart <hi>meet</hi> for ſuch a worſhip; and you commune with your owne heart upon your bed, enquiring what holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe you have gained by the <hi>Ordinances</hi> you now have; for they that are not good husbands, and thriving under theſe, I cannot tell whether they ſhall be truſted with greater matters. (5.) And to ſhutt up this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154605:22"/> If it be with you as aforeſaid, Then your heart is open, and your mouth open, and your purſe is open, and your hands hang not down; All you have, and all you are, ſhall be expended, laid out for <hi>Him,</hi> for His <hi>Name,</hi> for His cauſe, for His ſervants, All for Him, who hath ſo laid-forth all His Attributes for us, A falling, ſinking, dying Nation; All for Him, (forget it not) who remembred us <hi>in our low eſtate.</hi> All for Him. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I joyne with you heartily, and that is all the anſwer I can make to all the fore-mentioned. I muſt enquire further of you for reſolution now; The Government by Biſhops, it is gone, it is fallen like a <hi>great Milſtone;</hi> It <hi>ſhall be found no more in heaven,</hi> the Church, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are now two <hi>wayes</hi> of Government, (I expreſſe it as I can, and as I conceive it in the moſt popular way) The <hi>Presbyterian way;</hi> the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent way.</hi> The Adverſary meets mee in both wayes, croſſeth mee in the one, choakes mee in the other. I beſeech you, Sir, for Gods ſake, and His cauſe, be pleaſed to give mee ſatisfaction, that I may ſatisfie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who finding mee almoſt your <hi>Conver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Ile cut you ſhort there. I pray you doe not call your ſelfe my <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert.</hi> If the Word of GOD has not turned you, hold you where you firſt were, for Arch-biſhops, Lord, or Dioceſan-Biſhops, hold you there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>God forbid. But I pray you pardon the Word; It relates to you, but as to an inſtrument, and let mee goe on; My Adverſaries finding me a <hi>Convert,</hi> hitt mee in the teeth with this; You are for the <hi>Scotts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> the Presbyteriall-Government, a Rigid Government, worſe than the Biſhops, an Iron yoake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer them thus, but in the Spirit of meekneſſe; as you tender the Glory of GOD, and the good of His choſen; ſhew no heat in theſe matters; but tell them, They are cleane miſtaken. The <hi>Scotts Diſcipline</hi> is as neare, as their light has carried them, cloſe up to the Word of God; and as more light ſhall appeare, cloſer-up they will come. Tell them, God has appeared to that people in that <hi>way,</hi> wonderfully, marvai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly: And a great Reformation is wrought amongſt them, a great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation! And great things has the LORD wrought by them, and marvailous! And if wee <hi>trust</hi> not in them, if wee <hi>leane</hi> not on their <hi>arme,</hi> great things will they <hi>doe</hi> for us. But for their <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> ſay againe, That, were not the Pillars out of courſe; and the Lawes ſilent, becauſe the Trumpet is ſo loud; could their <hi>heads</hi> and <hi>leaders</hi> walke in the way with a <hi>right foote</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>, as the word is, and as they deſire to goe: could they keepe cloſe, and keepe their people cloſe, in this extravigant time, to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:154605:23"/> their owne rule, and principles; Then your Adverſaries now would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with you, and acknowledge, That they have, after their manner, blaſphemed the <hi>Scotts,</hi> and their <hi>way.</hi> Tell mee now, Doe you thinke that this I have ſaid will not ſtop the Adverſaries mouth, ſo wide open againſt the <hi>Scotts Diſcipline?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>No indeed; All this will not ſtop the mouth of the Adverſary. The reaſon is, Becauſe ſome mouthes will not be ſtopped, till they be wrapt-up in a winding ſheet, and ſtopped about with dirt. But you have anſwered mee, and I am ſatisfied at that point. My adverſary will meet mee at another point, and he will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fle mee there, or choake mee quite. He will tell mee, <q>You ſhall have Lords in every place more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute than was the <hi>Lord-Biſhop,</hi> for they will be more <hi>independent.</hi>
                  </q> That choaks me quite, I have not a word to reply. I entreat you, Sir, helpe mee here, and tell mee, what you thinke of that <hi>way,</hi> what is your judgement thereof, I meane judgement as wee ſpeake popularly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay well, elſe I ſhould have ſaid, who made mee a Judge? Indeed you ſhould not have craved my judgement, which is ſo low and ſmall, in ſo high and great matters. But fith you crave it, take it, as it is, and make the beſt of it: Thus I judge of the <hi>way;</hi> It is an excellent <hi>way,</hi> an heavenly <hi>way,</hi> a Church-way, an holy <hi>way:</hi> And the <hi>excellent</hi> of the earth walke in that <hi>way,</hi> and are for that <hi>way;</hi> and that is as much as I ſhall ſay concerning the <hi>way.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>It is enough; but you muſt make good what you ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>That needs not, and yet it ſhall be made manifeſt and apparent to your eyes, though I ſay no more; for what are words? The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of theſe men who are for this <hi>way,</hi> in their owne houſe, and in the houſe of GOD, this holds-forth their <hi>way</hi> to be an holy, an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, a Church-way, as was ſaid; there is the proofe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>It is indeed, and <hi>The Church in thy houſe</hi> is the praiſe in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. But is not the converſation of thoſe men, who are for the other <hi>way,</hi> as gracious, as holy, as Church-like, as is the converſation of theſe men who are for the <hi>Independent</hi> way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed my ſpirit is ſtirred, I had beſt to ſtop a while, leſt I fire up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, and word it with you, and ſo marre all—I doe bethink my ſelfe of the way we are upon; I muſt doe nothing unbeſeeming that way; elſe you ſhould heare words ſharp or <hi>cutting</hi> You would force <note place="margin">Tit 1. 13</note> me to make compariſons, they are odious, The converſation of the one and the other is Church-like, elſe they are not in a Church-way. I ſpake not words, but my heart before. I proteſt unto you, I doe ſo honour the <hi>Scots,</hi> and their <hi>way,</hi> that I can ſcarce keep my heart from
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154605:23"/> idolizing them in their way: And certainy, could it doe them any good, I could waſh their feet, and kiſſe them when I have done, ſuch love I beare to them and their <hi>way.</hi> You will give me leave now, ſith it is for your ſatisfaction, to tell you my judgement touching this <hi>way,</hi> and ſo I have done heartily: Now you would have me make compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: No but I will not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Pardon me, Sir, and teach me I pray you, what I ſhall anſwer to my adverſaries, who tell me that the men you ſo commend, are <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent.</hi> men. What ſhall I ſay to this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Tell your adverſaries, they are fouly miſtaken.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>The men ſay ſo themſelves, they call themſelves <hi>Independents.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>They doe not ſure. But you are a learner, beleeve me: The men that are for this way, are the moſt (I had like to have exceeded in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon) are as <hi>Dependent</hi> men, as any are in the world. They <hi>lean</hi> upon their <hi>beloved</hi> evermore; they ſeek counſell at his mouth evermore; they would not move a ſtep, nor ſpeake a word without him: they hearken diligently what their LORD ſaith: And they will hearken what any man, though the loweſt of men, any man ſhall ſay unto them from their LORDS mouth. They independent! How independent? As you and I are in our houſes; low and weak men, we, and yet wee will not ſuffer another man to <hi>Lord</hi> it over us in our houſe: for the Cook, they ſay, will not abide it in his Kitchin; ſo <hi>Independent</hi> we and the Cook are. And yet ſo dependent we are, that our practices, our duties, our Doctrines, &amp;c. are ſubject to the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Prophets, as they ſubmit themſelves to the <hi>Spirit</hi> breathing in the <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of all. I could wiſh heartily, a better and larger explication of this word, then here is time, or place, or ability to make: becauſe it is ſo generally miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtood, it ſhould have a more free and full explication.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>What ſay you to the gathering of Churches? The language of the times, and the practice of grave and learned Miniſters; what ſay you to it? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>a Matth.</hi> 24. 40. Luke 17. 34.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I will, in all meekneſſe and ſubmiſſion to better judgement, bolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out what I have conceived; That this <hi>ſeparating,</hi> this <hi>culling</hi> and <hi>gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> work, is reſerved for the Angels when GOD ſhall give them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, <note place="margin">b <hi>Hiphlah</hi> Pſaſ. 4. 3. Then the <hi>Lord</hi> ſets apart him that is godly for himſelfe.</note> and then a <hi>marvelous ſeparating</hi> ſhall be; for then <hi>Two ſhall be in one bed, &amp;c. the one ſhall be taken, the other left:</hi> ſo it will be then, a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering, a culling out one from another who ſtood before in the neereſt relation, were partakers of the ſame worke and reward, then a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not till then in an orderly way. Now husband, wife, child, and ſervant, all ſhould goe together to the ſame place, there to partake of the ſame ordinances.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:154605:24"/>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Very well: But then the wife that is ſpirituall, may partake of the ſame holy things with her husband, who is carnall: And the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that is the Lords free-man, may <hi>break bread</hi> with his maſter, who is to every good work <hi>reprobate.</hi> What ſay you to that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Not much, let the Paſtors or Miniſters look to that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>But here is a <hi>leaven</hi> now in our congregation, which <hi>leaveneth</hi> the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5 6</note> whole lump.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Search the Scriptures, and enquire wee of our Teachers whether that be the meaning, <hi>That another mans wickedneſſe can leaven you:</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire concerning that matter, you will read, <hi>To the clean all things are clean <hi rend="sup">•</hi>.</hi> I cannot think that unclean perſons, whom the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calls <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Swine,</hi> can pollute <hi>childrens bread</hi> to <hi>children.</hi> Ile tell <note place="margin">Tit 1. 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Luk. 11. 41 <hi>All things are clean unto you. Ne omnes Angelos, ſi Miſſa in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſint, &amp;c. Epiſt.</hi> 265.</note> you what <hi>Calvin</hi> ſayes; <q>My poſition is (ſaith he) that a pious or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred action cannot be defiled by the fault or pollution of men: And thus I uſe to cleare it; If all the Angels in heaven were preſent at the Maſſe (that abomination) they could not, with all their holineſſe, waſh off the filth of that Sacrifice; nor can all the Divels in hell (if preſent at the <hi>holy Supper)</hi> defile that ſacred Ordinance to me, received by me with pure hands, and a clean heart.</q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>If this gathering of Churches be according to the expreſſe <hi>Word</hi> of GOD, why ſhould you or any man be againſt it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>According to the word of God, and againſt it! God forbid, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſay, ſith there is an <hi>if</hi> in it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let us, ſimple ones, ſtay a while, till fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enquiry be made at Gods mouth, and reſolution given touching that matter, that ſo all <hi>(ifs)</hi> may be taken away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>But in the mean time here are <hi>two wayes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, ſeemingly, and no more: As two wayes upon a great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon or Heath, which anon will meet in one: or as two ſtreams which break the bank a little, and ſo run croſſe, but after a ſmall circuit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, meet again, running into the ſame channell. I leave theſe <hi>wayes</hi> under hope, and full perſwaſion, that a way ſhall be taken to cleare this <hi>word</hi> and <hi>way,</hi> from a ſure <hi>word,</hi> ſo as both <hi>wayes</hi> ſhall meet in one; and all that are ſeemingly divided there, ſhall kiſſe and embrace each other as brethren: for they ſhall enquire, not each of other, what is this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns way, or that mans way, but of GOD, and the <hi>word</hi> of GOD, they ſhall enquire <hi>what is</hi> GODS <hi>way, and the way of his people,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which they are charged, <hi>This is the way, walke in it.</hi> I have told you my hope, I will ſhew you the grounds of this hope. The firſt,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Wee have a promiſe, I <hi>will give them one heart and one way.</hi> A ſure <note place="margin">Ier. 32 39.</note> word; It is don; So The LORD ſpeaks of things to be don in His ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154605:24"/> time, the beſt time: God is <hi>one;</hi> The Lord Chriſt <hi>one;</hi> faith <hi>one;</hi> Church <hi>one;</hi> without doubt the <hi>way</hi> ſhall be <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>foole</hi> ſhall <note place="margin">Iſa 35. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>not erre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Wee ſee how the Aſſemblies both conſpire in one, To unite hearts and affections, and judgements, ſo to make all <hi>one!</hi> Wee ſee this, elſe wee ſee nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed I doe not ſee it, I can tell you that there are in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, ſome for this <hi>way,</hi> and ſome for that, and very eager and hot-ſpirited they are for their way, as was told me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>And you might tell your ſelfe; That Angells are not Aſſembled there, but men, ſubject <hi>to the like paſſions as wee are,</hi> and may declare them too openly as men doe. But this I can tell you, That theſe men who are indeed for a <hi>Church-way</hi> (an holy way what ever it be) and doe walke in it, have been greatly humbled for that eagerneſſe of ſpirit, if more than was fitting, which was declared in their contention for that <hi>way:</hi> And before they came to their ſeats next day, where they were a note too high, they were low in humiliation, they afflicted their ſoules for being ſo high the day before; And they have made their watch the ſtronger for after-time, and for ever. And this for mightie reaſons; (1) Becauſe they are contenders for a <hi>holy way;</hi> All muſt be don in an holy manner, Church-like. (2.) They know alſo, many there are, who watch <hi>for their holting.</hi> It is enough for Caution.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There are mightie wraſtlings, the wraſtlings of GOD, ſtrong prayers; His ſervants will <hi>not let their Lord alone;</hi> They will give their <hi>God no reſt. Jacob weeps</hi> and <hi>he prayes;</hi> God muſt anſwer him; <hi>Jacob</hi> will not leave His GOD, without He leaves a bleſſing behinde Him. Heare you what ſeeking, and knocking, and praying there is, <hi>Lord, give the Nobles and Worthies in their Aſſemblies, to be perfectly joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgement, for this one way; That the LORD may be one, and His Name one in all Congregations.</hi> It is don, ſeekers ſhall be obtainers. As <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſo the ſeed of <hi>Jacob</hi> never <hi>ſought God in vaine.</hi> God is appearing in His Glory, for the <hi>deſtitute</hi> are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate with Him; <hi>Now I will ariſe, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And indeed He <note place="margin">Pſal. 102. 17.</note> does ariſe in all His peoples ſight; and He has made bare His <hi>Arme,</hi> even His <hi>Right Arme,</hi> and has done valiantly; Let the ſervants of the LORD ſay ſo, even for what they have ſeene, though they ſhould live to ſee no more. Their fathers have ſowen prayers, and watered them with teares, and wee have reaped. What a returne of prayers have wee ſeene! O wonderfull! <hi>Jacob</hi> has prayed, and the ſeed of <hi>Jacob</hi> has pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>then He ſpake unto us</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Hoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a. 12. 4.</note>; Wee have the fruit of their prayers;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:154605:25"/> They prayed, <hi>Lord</hi> caſt-out the vile, ſet in their roome the precious; <note place="margin">Note, that they doe cauſe all the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, who have a 3d. <hi>way,</hi> the <hi>way</hi> of their own hearts, and that <hi>way</hi> they would goe.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord</hi> purge the Temple, the ſervices there; <hi>Lord</hi> give thy people pure <hi>Ordinances;</hi> So they prayed; Then the <hi>Lord ſpake unto us;</hi> and as He ſpake, ſo He has don in our Dayes, Bleſſed, bleſſed, bleſſed be His Name; Then <hi>He ſpake unto us.</hi> O what cauſe have wee every one of us, To make our hearts Temples, our houſes Churches, our lives living monuments of His prayſe, That a Church-way, and a Church-life, and Church-Ordinances, all holy, and pure, may meet together, and kiſſe each other, <hi>Amen,</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To take a view of what is ſaid, wee have ſeene the Biſhops way, the way of <hi>Caine;</hi> Waſting and deſtruction is there, their foot ſtands, even at this preſent, in the path <hi>of the deſtroyer;</hi> Yet the Biſhops have their Advocates, thoſe, who plead for them and their way. The ſober man has what to anſwer; And is ſhewen an <hi>excellent way,</hi> the <hi>old way.</hi> There is a <hi>parting</hi> in it, as wee obſerve, the ſame way compaſſing an hill, and meeting againe in the valley, for the eaſe of man and beaſt. <hi>[As a Beaſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 63. 14. <hi>Leniter et commodè duxit ut ſolet, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſu mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t is ardui.</hi> Iſa 63. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>goeth downe into the valley, ſo the LORD will have his people lead]</hi> This <hi>way</hi> is as it is called a Church-way, the <hi>way of Holineſſe.</hi> No Lion ſhall be there; The uncleane ſhall not paſſe-over it. And now that I have mentioned them, the <hi>uncleane,</hi> I come to the remainder of my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, The caſting-out of the Biſhops <hi>Curates,</hi> thoſe uncleane perſons, for <hi>like Biſhops, like Curates;</hi> called ſo in a contrarietie to their office, as a mountaine is called in a contrarietie to what it does; It has its name from <hi>motion,</hi> they ſay, but moves like a mountaine: So theſe <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates</hi> have their names, as <hi>Biſhops</hi> have theirs, from <hi>cure</hi> and <hi>care,</hi> and <hi>over-ſight,</hi> when they <hi>care</hi> for nothing, nor did <hi>overſee</hi> any thing, but their <hi>Rents, Tythes,</hi> and <hi>in comes:</hi> and to make proviſion for their <hi>luſts.</hi> Wee cannot thinke, that <hi>Wren</hi> or <hi>Pearce,</hi> (theſe were called <hi>Biſhops)</hi> would endure, their <hi>Curates</hi> ſhould be better than themſelves, but as themſelves, as brutiſh men, as drunken ſotts, as vile Prieſts, as treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Prophets, as looſe and ſwiniſh in their life, and then, more then probable, they will be <hi>Naballs</hi> at their death. And what are the people now, that their <hi>guides</hi> are <hi>blind</hi> and <hi>brutiſh;</hi> They muſt needs be ſo too; from <hi>the Prophets and Prieſts is prophaneneſſe gone forth into all the Land;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 23. 15.</note> They have <hi>leavened</hi> the Land with Atheiſme, abominable Idolatries, and Heatheniſh prophaneneſſes. And now <hi>all yee beaſts of the feild come</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa 56. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>to devoure;</hi> yea, <hi>all yee beaſts in the Forreſt.</hi> And ſo it is according to the good word of the LORD; for <hi>His watchmen are blind they are all igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>they are all dumbe doggs, they cannot barke, ſleeping, lying downe, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing to ſlumber.</hi> You ſee whom I meane by theſe <hi>Curates;</hi> I argue now for the caſting-of-them-forth.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:154605:25"/>
               <p>
                  <q>They that have committed the ſame abominations, which others, <note place="margin">It is argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the caſting-out of <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates.</hi> Jer. 29. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> having committed, have been <hi>roſted in the fire,</hi> and <hi>then made a curſe;</hi> Theſe ought to be <hi>thruſt-out</hi> of the Land, by the Law of the Land: But theſe <hi>Curates</hi> have committed ſuch abominations. Speake, have you any thing to ſay for them.</q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Not a word, I muſt not plead for them, whom God condemnes; You muſt make proofe, That ſo they have don, according to thoſe abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>They have committed villanies in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> adultery with their neighbours wives; They have ſpoken lying words, (God knowes how many,) They have blaſphemed God, and the King; they have pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted God, and his Day, and his Houſe, and all the honours and ſervices there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>You have ſaid, you have not proved.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>There is the cleareſt proofe of all this that can be deſired. A <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury</hi> is come-out already, where their names are upon everlaſting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and their horrible abominations regiſtred: That one <hi>Century,</hi> (a hundred) implies nine <hi>Centuries</hi> more, they make a <hi>Chiliad,</hi> a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. And certainly, had wee the names of thoſe, and their abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons regiſtred alſo, who are under the Kings protection, we ſhould have a booke, as large as that wee call the <hi>Centuries.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Now that their places, their wickedneſſe rather, have ſpewed-them-out, whither are they gone?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>To the place where ſuch men ſhall finde favour, to <hi>Oxford.</hi> They have proceeded to the higheſt degrees of wickedneſſe in the countries, they are <hi>Doctors</hi> in the <hi>Art</hi> of drinking, whoring, rioting, now they gone to <hi>Oxford,</hi> as we ſay, to proceed <hi>Doctors of Divinity;</hi> and thence diſperſed to thoſe ſeverall places, whence Gods faithfulleſt ſervants have been caſt-out, where they will drink the healths, for they cannot pray, of their good <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Maſters,</hi> and for the proſperity of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, now in <hi>Array</hi> againſt the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> for as thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies proſper, ſo the <hi>Curates</hi> ſhall proſper. But now we heare they ſhall be all ſummoned to make their appearance at <hi>Oxford:</hi> for as they have there a <hi>thing</hi> they call a <hi>Parliament,</hi> made-up as aforeſaid, for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the Lawes, and Liberties of the Kingdome: ſo there muſt bee an aſſembly of Divines too, ſuch as have been ſpued out of their places, for the eſtabliſhing of the religion ſo often proteſted for. Ah Lord! But I forbeare. <hi>The poore commit themſelves to the Lord, Thou ſhalt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>them from this generation for ever. The wicked walke on every ſide, when the vileſt men are ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lted.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:154605:26"/>
               <p> Theſe <hi>Curates,</hi> as unſavoury ſalt, are caſt-out of the Church; Now the Divell has admitted them into his Chappell: Let him take their <hi>Service</hi> too: For, as like Biſhops like Curates: ſo, like Curates like Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, abominable all. I argue for the caſting of it forth.</p>
               <p>This ſervice is <hi>Dogs-meat,</hi> it muſt be caſt-out to the Dogs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I could never think the <hi>Curates Service</hi> to be childrens meat, but never heard I the Curates ſervice called <hi>Dogs-meat</hi> before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, you imply as much your ſelfe, If not childrens meat, then whoſe meat? Dogs-meat, I think. But I argue it, <hi>Torn fleſh is Dogs-meat.</hi> The Curates ſervice is as <hi>Torne fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Prove that if you can, That the Curates ſervice is as <hi>Torn fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>The Curates Service is a <hi>torn,</hi> diſtracted ſervice; here is a peece, &amp; there is a peece; here is the former part, and there is the latter; here the firſt ſervice, &amp; there the ſecond ſervice; here read at the Desk; there ſaid in the Pulpit; thence drawn up to the Altar: here are <hi>ſaying</hi> prayers, there are <hi>tooting</hi> prayers, upon the Cymball and the Organ; here they roared like Beares, there they braied like Aſſes, and yet Divine ſervice, they ſay: But hearken what the LORD ſayes; As <hi>torn fleſh,</hi> Dogges <note place="margin">Exod. 22. 38. Mal. 1. 13</note> meat, ſo is theſe Curates Service unto Me, Doe you bring that which is <hi>torne</hi> to me? <hi>Caſt it to the Dogges.</hi> It is done, they have it at Oxford, and all over the Land; yea all over the Chriſtian world, where the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill hath his Chappell, and where theſe abominable <hi>Curates</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> are. Let them alone with their meat, no man envies them; no good man but pittieth them, yet let them alone, theſe Curates with their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice together.</p>
               <p>Now I muſt compleat my undertaking, and argue againſt the <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you explain your ſelfe, and tell us what theſe are?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>What they are! They are <hi>Neuters,</hi> a curſed generation of men, ſeem not to know their right hand from their left; not which way to <note place="margin">Who are <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>uters.</hi>
                  </note> turn. I can liken them to nothing ſo fit, as to a <hi>ſhadow</hi> of a man, a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuch as you may obſerve ordinary in <hi>Flanders;</hi> There is a <hi>thing</hi> they call a <hi>Chriſt</hi> on the left hand; another <hi>thing</hi> they call the <hi>virgin Mary</hi> on the right hand; and in the midſt, a <hi>third thing</hi> called a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> with this inſcription before him, <hi>Crime vortam neſcio.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Ile heare no more of that; ſuch a picture does not become your gravity, nor is it proper to the matter in hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I like your plainneſſe well, I ſpake it but to try how you had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited by all our diſcourſe hitherto. True it is, ſuch a picture gives us no inſtruction touching the ſubject in hand; for which way ſoever the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:154605:26"/> looker-on had turned, death was on either hand. But now take things as indeed they are, not repreſented to us, but indeed and in truth.</p>
               <p>Here is the <hi>Living God,</hi> the Lord Chriſt, and his Truths on the right hand. Here is the Devill, his Pope and his Biſhops with all their blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, on the other hand; yet, <hi>cui me vortam neſcio,</hi> the man is not yet reſolved what hand to take, <hi>he is a Neuter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, here is on the right hand, a <hi>Parliament</hi> called together by the King himſelfe, acknowledged a Parliament, confirmed and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed a Parliament by his own hand: On the left hand there are <hi>Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies</hi> of (Robbers) which they call a Parliament (in Oxford) made up of the <hi>refuſe</hi> and <hi>garbage</hi> of the land, and yet, <hi>cui me vortam neſcio,</hi> to what hand he may turne, he cannot tell. <hi>This is a Neuter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, here are, on the right hand, Nobles and Worthies, who have approved themſelves true Patriots, zealous of Gods honour, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to their King and Kingdome; who can have no other end, as is cleare to all the Chriſtian world, but the peace of the Church, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſafety of the King and Kingdome, no other end: On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand are, left-handed men, robbers, ſpoilers, murtherers, unjuſt men, <hi>who know no ſhame,</hi> who are as roaring Lions, and devouring Wolves, to the inhabitants all over the land; yet, <hi>cui me vortam neſcio,</hi> he knowes not to which ſide he ſhould joyne; <hi>he is a Neuter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Here are a generation of <hi>Seekers,</hi> who ſeek God day &amp; night, who have commanded us as Q. <hi>Eſter</hi> her people, <hi>Goe, aſſemble your ſelues</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſt. 4. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>together, faſt and pray for us, we alſo will doe likewiſe,</hi> theſe are on the right hand: On the left hand there is the Prince of Robbers, Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, they that curſe and ſweare, and blaſpheme all the day long; yet, <hi>cui me vortam neſcio,</hi> to what hand to turn hee knowes not, <hi>Hee is a Neuter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſpeak yet more plainly, and according to the expreſſe word of God. <hi>They are Neuters who come not out to help the Lord againſt the mighty;</hi> mighty <hi>Nimrods,</hi> mighty hunters before the LORD, men <hi>skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to deſtroy</hi> the Faith, Religion, Lawes, Liberties of the Kingdome; mighty hunters before the Lord; yet theſe will not come forth to help the Lord at ſuch a time as this; no though the <hi>Lord</hi> calls to them now, <hi>Who will riſe up for me againſt the evill doers? Or who will ſtand up for me</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 94. 16</note> 
                  <hi>against the workers of iniquity?</hi> Theſe will not, <hi>theſe are Neuters.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Poſſibly, nay probably theſe may not know that things are as they are; things are repreſented to them otherwiſe, as they have heard it <hi>declared</hi> and <hi>proteſted</hi> more than ſeven times; <hi>They may not know.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>What may they not know? They doe know that <hi>Ireland</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154605:27"/> They doe know that this viperous generation is eating-out the heart and bowels of the Kingdome; They doe know that the <hi>Faith, Religion,</hi> Lawes and Liberties of the Kingdome are deſtroyed under a colour and ſemblance of maintaining the ſame. They doe know, &amp;c. But I will tell you a ſtory firſt; <q>That notable murtherer, who ſtab'd K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> was examined whether hee did not make known his purpoſe to his Ghoſtly Father, his Confeſſor; Hee anſwered, <hi>Yes;</hi> His Confeſſor, a Jeſuit, was examined at that point; he anſwered, he did not know (that is, to tell them) but very likely, ſaid he, the intention was made known unto me, under the Roſe, and I have a gift (of the ſpirit) preſently to forget what is told me under the ſeale of Confeſſion.</q> My Author is not at hand, nor doe I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how they dealt with him; but certainly, they took a ready way to quicken his memory before hee was cut aſunder: ſo it muſt be here, Theſe men pretend they know not this, and they know not that, They will not know, or they will not know to tell us. But they diſſemble in all that they ſay; They doe know that the Kings foot ſtands up to the knees in blood, <hi>in the path of the deſtroyer.</hi> They doe know, that he has caſt forth all the pretious Miniſters of Juſtice, and Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, where his hand could reach; and thruſt in the vile into their places; They doe know what the Queen has done beyond the ſeas, what <hi>Digby</hi> with her favourites (her Agents and factors for <hi>Babylon)</hi> what theſe have done there, and what they are doing here; They doe know what is in deſigne, how bloody the adverſaries intentions are, and that they have ſlain the ſervants of the Lord with a rage that <hi>reacheth up to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en</hi> ſo high muſt their judgement reach: This they doe know. They doe know that the King has made peace with his worſt enemies, &amp; is at warres with, and bids defiance to his beſt friends. They doe know, That the King is plucking down his own houſe; That he has thruſt away the great ſupporters of his Throne, <hi>Iudgement</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice.</hi> They do know what the King has proteſted, proclaimed, declared to all the world; And they doe know what his <hi>Commiſſions</hi> have been, how bloody, how deſtructive. They doe know how that <hi>Bristoll</hi> is given into the enemies hands, and they doe heare that the Queen ſhall have a Chappell there: They doe heare the groanes of the priſoners, and the cries of the poore becauſe of their Taskmaſters: for their oppreſſion is more grievous than is, or ever was, the Turkiſh or Egyptian ſlavery. They doe know, which way the Devill, and all his miniſters doe draw, now, and yet they withdraw themſelves as men that know not which way to turn, <hi>They are Neuters.</hi> Hang them, cut <hi>them aſunder.</hi> It is the ſentence from the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:154605:27"/> law of <hi>Nature,</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> of <hi>Armes:</hi> It is the ſentence from the law of God too.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is againſt the law of <hi>Nature,</hi> that they who are without naturall affection, ſhould enjoy the common gifts of nature, <hi>light, water, fire.</hi> Againſt the law of <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Arms,</hi> that thoſe ſubjects ſhould enjoy the priviledges and communities of ſubjects, who ſee with open face, the adverſary and enemy deſtroying all theſe, and hold their hands in their pockets the while. Againſt the <hi>law</hi> of GOD, that they who ſee the <hi>Lawes, Rights, Liberties</hi> of his kingdome trampled upon by ſwine, and yet ſtand <hi>Neuters,</hi> that they ſhould not feel the ſharpeſt puniſhment. I will argue theſe things in order.</p>
               <p>They that are the ſame, and have done the ſame which he did, and for <note place="margin">It is argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the caſting-out of <hi>Neuters.</hi>
                  </note> doing ſo was plucked a ſunder with two Teemes of Horſes, four Horſes in a Teeme, do deſerve to be caſt out of the land by the law of the land. But theſe <hi>Neuters</hi> are the ſame as he was, and do the ſame as he did, for which he was ſo puniſhed. Therefore, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To relate to a more known ſtory, They that are the ſame, and have done the ſame, and for doing whereof, others, their fellow-brethren, have had their skin torne from their fleſh, and their fleſh from their bones, theſe doe deſerve to be caſt-out of the land: But theſe are the ſame, and doe the ſame which they did, who, in former time, were ſo puniſhed. Therefore theſe ought to bee caſt-out by the law of the Land.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They that are the ſame, and doe the ſame, which they did, who were curſed from Gods mouth, and commanded to be curſed by all the people theſe ought to be caſt-out of the land by the law of the land. But theſe are the ſame, and doe the ſame, which they did, who were ſo curſed. Therefore, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Prove that theſe <hi>Neuters</hi> now, doe now as they did in ancient times.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>They doe now the ſame thing: for they get to an upper-place (in <note place="margin">Metius Suffetius.</note> ſpeculation) as he did ſpying which ſide is ſtrongeſt, and likelieſt to prevaile; and to that ſide they will <hi>wheel</hi> about anon. But that is too farre of; I will take that which is neerer the eye. Theſe men doe as the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> did, therefore theſe are as the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> were, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I can ſay nothing to that; I know not what the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> were; or whether there were ſuch a people in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>It is your ignorance, and not to be excuſed; you know not the Scriptures, and therefore your workes muſt needs be bad, and you muſt walke as a man in the darke; It is a very famous ſtory, touching the men of <hi>Succoth,</hi> Ile relate it as briefly as I can.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:154605:28"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Gideon</hi> and his three hundred men were <hi>faint,</hi> yet <hi>purſuing</hi> after <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ba</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 8. 4, 5.</note> and <hi>Zalmunna,</hi> Kings of <hi>Median, Iſraels</hi> enemies: <hi>And he ſaid to the men of Succoth, give, I pray you, loaves unto the people that follow mee, for they are faint: Gideon</hi> told them alſo, (as is likely) That he would requite their kindneſſe when God had delivered his enemies-up into his hands, whereof <hi>Gideon</hi> made no queſtion. The Princes of <hi>Succoth,</hi> living at eaſe, and faring deliciouſly, hearkned not to <hi>Gideon,</hi> nor regarded how faint his men were: They mock and jeere at <hi>Gideon;</hi> Yes, ſay they, you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne us our bread when you have your enemies in your hands; When will that be? That is a doubtfull caſe; wee will not part with our bread upon ſuch an hazard. You thinke your ſelfe as ſure of your enemies, as if you had them in your hands; you ſee not at what diſadvantage you ſtand, wee doe ſee it: Your enemies are Kings, Kings will helpe one the other, They have power, you are weake and faint; You have not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of neceſſaries, and thinke you to overcome two Kings? There is a great peradventure. Wee will ſee the buſineſſe cleared, and the doubt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, then wee ſhall know what is beſt for us to doe; If you have the victory over the <hi>Kings,</hi> then you ſhall have our bread; If the Kings have victory over you, then they ſhall have our bread. Goe-on now and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, faint you may, and fall downe, and ſtarve for us; you get no bread of us; wee will not part with it at a peradventure; You queſtion not the victory; It is a great queſtion to us; <hi>Are the heads of Zeba and Zalmunna</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 6.</note> 
                  <hi>in thy hands, that wee ſhould give bread unto thine Army?</hi> This ſtory is as ſoone underſtood as read; &amp; as eaſily applied to our <hi>neuters</hi> now adayes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Very well; But how prove you, That <hi>neuters</hi> were ſo grievouſly puniſhed in ancient dayes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I prove it firſt out of the <hi>Romane Chronicle;</hi> The body of <hi>Metius Suffetius,</hi> who ſtood <hi>neuter,</hi> to ſpy which fide was ſtrongeſt, that thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he might turne, was adjudged by a Councell of warre, to have his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy tyed unto two teemes of foure horſes, which <hi>halled</hi> contrary wayes; So his body was drawne aſunder, and plucked into two peeces accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>What have Chriſtians to doe with what the <hi>Romans</hi> did? It was the firſt and laſt puniſhment that ever the <hi>Romanes</hi> executed with ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reſpect, or none at all, To the Lawes of humanitie, ſayes the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian himſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Well then, let it goe, though it inſtructs us very well, what may lawfully be don to <hi>neuters</hi> now adayes. But wee muſt not ſo lightly paſſe over what we reade in the ſacred Text, upon which wee were even now, and muſt ſet a marke. Wee reade, how the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> jeered and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:154605:28"/> 
                  <hi>Gideon;</hi> Now reade what <hi>Gideon</hi> replies to them; <hi>Therefore when the Lord hath delivered Zeba and Zalmunna into mine hands, then will I teare your fleſh with the thornes of the Wilderneſſe, and with briars.</hi> And as he threatned to deale with them, ſo he did deale; <hi>He tooke the Elders of the Citie, and thornes of the Wilderneſſe, and briars, and with them he taught the men of Succoth.</hi> He taught them! A ſore Teaching! but very exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary for theſe men in our dayes, They <hi>that will not be taught with words, muſt be taught with paine.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, but <hi>Gideons</hi> teaching is no rule for us ſo to teach; he taught with <hi>briars</hi> and <hi>thornes,</hi> wee muſt be more mercifull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>More mercifull! mercy to the wicked is crueltie to the good: pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to Gods enemies is but a fruit of bitter hatred to His friends. But I will paſſe over that too, yet wee muſt not paſſe over, but obſerve with all obſervation, what the LORD ſayes; <hi>Curſe you Meroz, ſaid the Angel of the Lord; Curſe yee bitterly the Inhabitants thereof.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you, what was this <hi>Meroz?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Surely, I cannot tell; An obſcure people they were, they had no relation to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> farther than that they were men, partaking of the ſame common nature, neere adjoyning to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and beholding the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe; lookers-on, when mightie Adverſaries were before them; <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods people, diſtreſſed behinde them, yet <hi>lookers on Iſraels affliction, in the day of their calamitie;</hi> beholding it with the eye, but not regarding it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Was that all?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>All! It was enough to bring a curſe, and to make it cleave unto them for ever; <hi>Therefore curſe yee Meroz, never ceaſe</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Indeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenter,</hi> Jun.</note> 
                  <hi>calling for a curſe, till the curſe come;</hi> In <hi>curſing curſe yee him, becauſe they came not out to help the Lord againſt the mightie.</hi> The diſtreſſe of a perſon, or a people, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to command pitty: If a perſon or people be fallen into the hands <note place="margin">The day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles, is a diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering day. When <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into the hands of theeves, (the prince of robbers) hee ſhall know who is his neighbour</note> of theeves: But I will not make an <hi>if</hi> of the matter; That, which was a parable anciently, is a truth now, &amp; relates to <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> both, Theſe two Nations are fallen into <hi>the hands of theeves,</hi> God ſo diſpoſing and ſuffering it to be Now woe to the lookers-on, and <hi>paſſers</hi> by on the other ſide, woe to them. Now is the diſtinguiſhing time, now wee ſhall know our friends, who is our neighbour and our brother; he that <hi>ſhewes mercy, he is the neighbour,</hi> though the adverſary and enemy ſayes, <hi>He is a Samaritan and has a Devill.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>By this account now, which you have given of <hi>Meroz,</hi> and of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> in diſtreſſe, fallen into the hands of Theeves, <hi>Zealand</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> ſhould come-in now to help <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>That they ſhould ſure, ſtronger bonds and engagements are upon
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:154605:29"/> them, then was upon <hi>Meroz.</hi> Stronger, ſaid I? I ſhould have ſaid more: But I forbeare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>What means it then, that they have ſhipped over their Artillery, inſtruments of death, to furniſh the enemy and adverſary?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt lay the blame of that—upon the Devils inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ungratefull wretches, there and here, and every where, lay that—upon them, and not upon the countrey, or people. The adverſary prevailed there, and thruſt forth a ſhip or two fraighted as wee know; but doubtleſſe the <hi>Hollanders</hi> doe know what the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have done for them, to render them a <hi>free People:</hi> they will not ſend over inſtruments of death therewith to cut <hi>Engliſh</hi> throats, or to make them ſlaves; they abhor the thoughts of ſuch a requitall for old unrecountable favours from the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> How much <hi>Engliſh</hi> noble blood hath been ſhed to maintain their cauſe! How much?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>Embaſſadours are now come to mediate a peace, they ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>A peace! What, &amp;c. all the world knowes what followes, God is making inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for blood: he will require it at the hands of them that ſhed it. And now the <hi>Parliament</hi> cannot take it ill that they are not treated with about the thing ſome call <hi>Peace:</hi> The GOD of gods, KING of kings, and LORD of Lords, is not treated with. And yet when he giveth quietneſſe, who can make trouble? And when he hideth his face, who can behold him, whether it be done againſt a nation, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Iob. 34. 29.</note> a man only? To ſhut-up all: Thus we have concluded from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtion'd premiſſes, That though <hi>Holland</hi> hold their peace, and <hi>ſtand-Neuters,</hi> as <hi>Meroz</hi> did, <hi>Yet enlargement and deliverance ſhall ariſe to the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſt. 4. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Church of England from another place.</hi> It is a comfortable promiſe, <hi>Hee ſhall ſend from heaven and ſave me. England</hi> ſhall be ſaved, the Church <note place="margin">Pſal. 57. 3.</note> there ſhall have a glorious ſalvation, that it ſhall. But yet God and man expects neighbours ſhould ſhew themſelves neighbours. And who knowes whether all the kindneſſe <hi>England</hi> ſhewed to <hi>Holland,</hi> was not for <hi>ſuch a time as this.</hi> But if this move not, ſurely the curſe upon <hi>Meroz</hi> (well thought on) will move; A curſed generation, curſed from Gods mouth, and commanded to be curſed by all the people of God, <hi>Curſe ye Meroz, ſaid the Angel of the Lord, curſe yee bitterly the inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 5. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe they came not to the help of the</hi> LORD, <hi>to the help of the</hi> LORD <hi>againſt the mighty.</hi> So ſhall all thine enemies periſh, O <hi>Lord,</hi> they ſhall leave their names for a curſe to poſterity: But they that love thy <hi>Name,</hi> ſhall be as the morning light, which increaſeth more and more till the perfect day. So be it. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
